<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A relation of the state of the court of Rome made in the year 1661. at the council of Pregadi. By the most excellent, the Lord Angelo Corraro, ambassador from the most serene republique of Venice to Pope Alexander VII. Translated our of Italian by J.B. Gent.</title>
            <title>Relazione della corte romana fatta l'anno 1661. English</title>
            <author>Ferrare du Tot, Charles de, d. 1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1664</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 201 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 64 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A80585</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6344B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200886</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896878</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896878</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135322</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A80585)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135322)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2463:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A relation of the state of the court of Rome made in the year 1661. at the council of Pregadi. By the most excellent, the Lord Angelo Corraro, ambassador from the most serene republique of Venice to Pope Alexander VII. Translated our of Italian by J.B. Gent.</title>
                  <title>Relazione della corte romana fatta l'anno 1661. English</title>
                  <author>Ferrare du Tot, Charles de, d. 1694.</author>
                  <author>Correr, Angelo, 1605-1678, attributed name.</author>
                  <author>Bulteel, John, fl. 1683.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 109, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by T. Mabb, and are to be sold by Michael Young at the Blew Bible in Bedford-street in Covent-Garden; and John Playfere, at the White Bear in the Upper Walk of the New-Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by John Bulteel, of "Relazione della corte romana fatta l'anno 1661", previously attributed to Angelo Correr, and now unanimously considered to be by Charles du Tot. (Cf. Diz. biog. degli Italiana, v. 29, p. 483.).</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of: Rome exactly describ'd.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Rome (Italy) --  History --  1420-1798 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:1"/>
            <p>A RELATION Of the State of the COURT OF ROME, Made in the Year 1661. at the Council of <hi>Pregadi.</hi> By the Moſt Excellent, the Lord <hi>ANGELO CORRARO,</hi> Ambaſſador from the moſt <hi>Serene Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique</hi> of <hi>Venice</hi> to Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VII. Tranſlated out of <hi>Italian</hi> By <hi>J. B.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Mabb,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Michael Young</hi> at the <hi>Blew Bible</hi> in <hi>Bedford-ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden;</hi> and <hi>John Playfere,</hi> at the <hi>White Bear</hi> in the <hi>Upper Walk</hi> of the <hi>New-Exchange.</hi> 1664.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Sept.</hi> ult. 1663.</date>
               <signed>Roger L' Eſtrang.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:2"/>
            <head>To M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>MATTHIAS</hi> Van <hi>BEUNINGEN.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Relation, which cannot but divertiſe you may ſerve for Inſtruction, to many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who talk at preſent of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:135322:3"/> themſelves to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Cauſes and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of the Murther committed on the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of <hi>France.</hi> Truly, that act was very ſtrange: a great King to be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly wronged out of a Frolick, and thoſe Sage Worldlings ſeem to have renounced both their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Judgment, ſince they yet ſpeak of ìt ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fingly; they fancy and ſay, all will be made up again; that the buſineſs at laſt will come to a Negotiation, where the <hi>French</hi> cannot fail of having ſatisfaction:
<pb facs="tcp:135322:3"/> How can thoſe wiſe Heads ponder ſo long upon one thing? they will cut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out ſome other work; they will evaporate their Choller in ſinging fine Songs of us, their fury will vaniſh, and he that had the blows may bear them; the King ſhall be ſatisfi'd with the hanging up of three or four Catch pole Serjeants; and if at laſt, thoſe raſh ones ſhould put the buſineſs home, the Emperour and other Princes, whom the Pope is ſure of, will not fail their Holy Mother at her need: and then do they
<pb facs="tcp:135322:4"/> count it nothing to have Eight Red Hats to beſtow, and with the which they might—; But let thoſe Miniſters ſtand faſt? If the wound can be healed with words, ſo much the better, thoſe Bagatels will ſerve. However, Sir, I do not think I acquit my ſelf of what I owe you, nor do I pretend you ſhould be obliged to me, when I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent you with a Book that comes from your own Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, and can teach you no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing new. You are, Sir, of an Illuſtrious Family, where Virtue, Science, Politneſs,
<pb facs="tcp:135322:4"/> Riches, Reputation, and the moſt Refined Judgment in Affairs of State, are Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and Hereditary. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuſpected of flattery herein, ſince I have Crown'd Heads and Sovereign Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for my Witneſſes, whom, as I may ſay, have found themſelves honoured by the Embaſſies and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments wherein your Eldeſt Brother acquitted himſelf with no leſs praiſe to him, than ſatisfaction to them: this is no more then was ſaid by the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and is yet ſpoken of in <hi>France.</hi> Nevertheleſs,
<pb facs="tcp:135322:5"/> I believed this Treatiſe, which is no leſs curious than ſolid, deſerved to bear the name of a Perſon that hath acquired ſo much Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Commerce of all the Learned, by Travail, by choice Books, by his good Nature, and the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Reception he gives to all Studìous men. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors name ſpeaks his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, it is the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Senator <hi>Corraro,</hi> for whom there are no Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments too high in <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> that Politique Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, who judges of the Mindes of Men with a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty
<pb facs="tcp:135322:5"/> worthy his penetrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the judgment of a Man thorowly verſed in the affairs of the world, and with that liberty of truth natural to all Republicans. I beſeech you, Sir, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of my reſpects, and give me ſome tokens of your good-will by honouring me with your Commands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:6"/>
            <list>
               <head>A TABLE.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>AQuaviva</hi> 62</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aldobrandino</hi> 65</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aſtalli</hi> 70</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ALbici</hi> 71</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Azzolino</hi> 72</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Berenice</hi> 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bichi</hi> Card. 23</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bichi</hi> Prior. 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bandinelli</hi> 33</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barberino</hi> Fran. 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barberino</hi> Ant. 41</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brancaccio</hi> 44</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Barberino</hi> Char. 63</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Boromeo</hi> 69</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bagni</hi> 74</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bonviſi</hi> 76</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Corrado</hi> 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colonne</hi> 42</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Carpegna</hi> 45</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Coſtaguti</hi> 57</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cibo</hi> 62</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Donghi</hi> 58</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eſte</hi> 56</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elci</hi> 75</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fagnano</hi> 33</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Franciotti</hi> 43</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Filormarini</hi> 46</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Facchinetti</hi> 48</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Farneſe</hi> 76</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>France</hi> 83</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chigi</hi> Auguſta. 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chigi</hi> Mar. 16</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chigi</hi> Flav. 17</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chigi</hi> Auguſtin. 20</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chigi</hi> Sig. 23</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ginetti</hi> 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Giorio</hi> 48</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grinaldi</hi> 50</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gabrieli</hi> 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gondi</hi> 62</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gualtieri</hi> 66</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Genois</hi> 98</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>Harach <hi>44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Homodei <hi>59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The</hi> Cardinal Lantgrave of Heſſe <hi>72</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Imperiale</hi> 69</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Empire</hi> 80</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:8"/>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lugo</hi> 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ludoviſio</hi> 60</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Mario</hi> 14</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Medicis Charls</hi> Cardinal. 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maculano</hi> 47</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mazarin</hi> 50</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>D. Medicis John.</hi> 60</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maldachino</hi> 67</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Modena</hi> 100</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mantoua</hi> 101</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Odeſcalco</hi> 67</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ottobuono</hi> Ib.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>The <hi>Pope</hi> 3</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pallavicino</hi> 30</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pallotta</hi> 45</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pio</hi> 64</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:135322:8"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paulucci</hi> 75</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pologna</hi> 95</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Parma</hi> 99</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> 78</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roſpiglioſi</hi> 29</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roſſetti</hi> 49</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rondanini</hi> 57</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Raggi</hi> 59</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spada</hi> Virg. 34</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spada</hi> de Breſi ghele. 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sachetti</hi> 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Santa Croce</hi> 61</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spada</hi> of <hi>Luca</hi> 66</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sforza</hi> 73</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sagredo</hi> 77</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spain</hi> 89</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Savoy</hi> 96</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:9"/>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Triumvirat, vide</hi> C. A. I.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Toſcany</hi> 97</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin</hi> 55</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vidman</hi> 65</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Venice</hi> 102</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:9"/>
            <head>A RELATION Of The State of the <hi>CO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RT</hi> Of ROME.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Cannot but acquit my ſelf of what is due from all thoſe, who having finiſhed the employment wherewith your <hi>Serene Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique</hi> hath honoured them, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning back to their Country, bring home with them the Fruit they have gleaned in their Obſervations on the Forms of Government; the Deſigns and Maxims of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135322:10"/> thoſe Princes near whom they have reſided, together with all ſuch other things as they eſteem moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be known, and noted by your Excellencies.</p>
            <p>I ſhall be brief in the quantity of things I have to ſay, reducing them to what is moſt eſſential, that thereby they may be the more firmly imprinted in your Memories, and ſhall make but three Chapters of them.</p>
            <p>In the Firſt, I ſhall treat of the Nature, the Qualities, the Paſſions, the Inclinations, and the Deſigns of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> VII, the Kindred of his <hi>Holineſs</hi> who have part in the Government, and his other Confidents, to whom he is accuſtomed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the moſt important intereſts of the Papacy.</p>
            <p>In the Second, I ſhall ſpeak of the College of the Cardinals, and give an account in ſhort of the Intereſts, and the good and bad Qualities of each of them.</p>
            <p>In the Third, I will declare the reaſons, by which one may conclude, whether the Pope have any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to love one Nation more than another; And I promiſe your Excellencies, the ſame Sincerity and the ſame Indifferency, which in ſo many years Service as I have rendred you, may have made you know is become natural to me, and without which I can undertake nothing, without putting a conſtraint or force upon my humor.</p>
            <p>I ſhould never have enter'd upon the particulars of the Behaviour, the Paſſions and Qualities of the preſent Pope, if any other had done it before me: But ſeeing the Lord <hi>Sagredi</hi> left <hi>Rome</hi> in the firſt year of this Pope's Aſſumption, at which time his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs profeſſed to have Sentiments quite contrary to what appeared the years following: and that the Lord <hi>Girolamo Giuſtincani,</hi> who was able to have
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135322:10"/> exactly obſerved, and ſounded all theſe ſecrets, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed a few months after he had begun his em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and ſo could not therein ſhow the heighth and ſagacity of his Wit. I find my ſelf obliged to undertake ſo important a Work, ſo much the more difficult, as being extremly nice, and very eaſie to be miſtaken, becauſe of the profeſſion every one makes at <hi>Rome</hi> to keep his inclinations ſo conceal'd, that it ſhould be impoſſible to diſcover them.</p>
            <p>BEginning then with the Exterior parts, which are moſt eaſie to be known, for I ſhall penetrate into the Interior afterwards. Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the VII, who at preſent ſits in the Chair, was born at <hi>Siena,</hi> the ſixth day of <hi>February,</hi> in the year 1599, ſo that he hath paſſed the one and ſixtieth year of his age on the ſame day of this preſent year 1660. It is now the ſixth year of his being Pope, which began on the ſeventh day of this preſent month of <hi>April.</hi> This Pope does not enjoy a health which can be called perfect, becauſe it is ſubject to divers ſuch alterations, as do not ordinarily give us any hopes of a long life. The firſt is a great Humidity of the Brain, which obliges him to keep his head ever very Hot. Nor does this ſuffice to hinder the bad effects of it; ſince his teeth being ſpoiled and loſt by the continual defluxion which fell upon them, he hath ſo few left, that if he had not ſupplied that want, by cauſing Artificial ones to be ſet in their ſtead, it would be a great hindrance to his ſpeech: Nor does he ſpeak plain with all this Art, and not being able therewith to chaw ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, he is neceſſitated to eat onely Liquid things, which have no need of being chewed; and although they ſhould naturally be of a more eaſie digeſtion, yet experience tells us, that they do not always ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135322:11"/> with him, ſince he is ſubject to indiſpoſitions and qualms in his ſtomach, which can be attributed to nothing but indigeſtion, the debility of his natural heat hindring the concoction of ſuch nouriſhing meats as they ordinarily feed him with. Exerciſe, however, does him good, for he walks in the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, and in his Garden, and ſometimes a foot in thoſe Streets that are the leaſt frequented about the City. He finds eaſe likewiſe in Purgations, for which purpoſe he ordains the Retreat he makes in the Campagnia of <hi>Rome,</hi> both Spring and Fall. From all which it happens, that being aſſaulted on the one ſide by the weakneſs of his Complexion, and upheld on the other hand by all that the Art and Induſtry of Man can invent, he may hold out poſſibly to the three and ſixtieth year of his age, which will be his Climaterical, for at that time are thoſe bad humors principally encreaſed and ſtirred up. He is not free from the pain of the Stone, which is ſo ordinary at <hi>Rome,</hi> being very often tormented with the difficulty of making Urine by certain little Stones, which are ſooneſt bred in thoſe of a delicate conſtitution, and who apply themſelves to buſineſs. For it is certain, that none can tie themſelves to it more than the Pope does, who hardly lets paſs any morning with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving audience, employing the remainder of the day in the diſcuſſion of the moſt knotty affairs. And although he does ſometimes divertiſe his more troubled and wearied thoughts by Entertainments of <hi>Literature,</hi> as of <hi>Poetry, Hiſtory</hi> or <hi>Policy</hi> amongſt Learned men; it is nevertheleſs impoſſible but his Spirits muſt then likewiſe be very buſie and intent, in making reflexions on the choice diſcourſes have been held before him; to which muſt be added ſuch things as ſometimes diſquiet him; ſo that it is no
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135322:11"/> wonder, if with all this a complexion of it ſelf but feeble, cannot ſuffice to all that is neceſſary for the functions of his natural life.</p>
            <p>The Pope is of a ſtature rather low than midling, of a black hair, which never till now began to turn gray, and, which is a ſign of the debility of his natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral heat, his skin is white, inclining a little to the Leaden colour, which is likewiſe another convincing proof of that diſpoſition I have before noted. He loves neatneſs, and indeed an extraordinary decency in all things, but particularly in his diet and cloaths; and therefore the care and induſtry of thoſe that cover his Table, and make ready his Viands, is ſo great, that they omit nothing imaginable, for the leaſt fault, either in the Meats themſelves, or the Dreſſing of them, were enough to anger him. But for his Cloaths, he is as curious of the beſt Linnen, as if he were yet in the flower of his Youth; nor does it ſuffice him to be cloathed in the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſit Cloth, but he muſt have his Garments en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with all the Adornments that can give them moſt luſtre and price: as it is well known that when he goes into the Country, he wears ſome that are garniſhed with little Diamond Buttons, and other Ornaments, both Coſtly and Magnificent. He hath the ſame curioſity for the Places he dwells in, and pleaſeth himſelf wonderfully in fair Houſes, which are ſo contrived as to bring in the Light on every ſide, and where nothing more can be deſired either in the Structure or the Ornament; which is the cauſe, that in the Houſe whether he retires in Spring and Autumn, he was not contented with what <hi>Urban</hi> had done, but hath added new quarters to it, and changed thoſe that were there already, that it might be magnificent and Royal. He hath
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135322:12"/> enlarged the Palace of the <hi>Quirinal</hi> with fair and long Apartments, for the uſe of ſuch as belong to the Popes Houſe, having had as little regard for the great expences required in the conſtruction of thoſe Edifices, as if he had Mines of Gold, or as if the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of the Eccleſiaſtical State had conſiſted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. But the Popes pleaſure is not bounded with the enlarging and embelliſhing onely of the Papal Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, he ſhows the ſame paſſion for the whole City. And thus it being in his thoughts and deſign to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſh it in the ſame manner, as thoſe <hi>Roman</hi> Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors formerly with much care and heat endeavoured to do, to wit, <hi>Auguſtus, Veſpaſian, Domitian,</hi> and others, he hath given full power to the Magiſtrate, who hath the office of ſurveying the Streets, to pull down Houſes and Palaces, where he judges the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency and ornament of the City does require it. So that, in effect, one may ſee them very buſie every day in demoliſhing of antient Structures, either to make ſome places the more ſpacious &amp; uniform, or to open a fitter way to ſome new ſtreets, and to that purpoſe there is a Tax impoſed on the neighbouring Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, which obliges the Proprietors to pay to thoſe, whoſe Houſes have been pulled down, a ſum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionate to their value. And the Pope does ſo much delight herein, that as long as his time laſts, he will not abſtain from making theſe changes, there being never want of occaſion, either to remove, or to rebuild in a City, where in the time the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians</hi> poſſeſſed it, the Houſes were raiſed without any Symmetry, onely for the convenienee of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants; and from this ariſes ſo many complaints in the City, that without any neceſſity, onely for the fancy and pleaſure of the Pope, and ſometimes of his Miniſters, many Families, that have but mean For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135322:12"/> ſhould feel the weight of ſuch grand Pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, which brings them neither benefit nor con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency in return. But that which exceeds all theſe exceſſive Expences, is, what he hath beſtowed upon that great and vaſt maſſie <hi>Portico</hi> which he hath undertaken to raiſe round about the place of the <hi>Baſilique Vaticane,</hi> for having changed the Deſign that famous Architect <hi>Michael Angel B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>onarota</hi> had formerly laid, who wrought with ſo much ſucceſs at the ſame Temple of St. <hi>Peters,</hi> and reduced this work to one range of <hi>Porticosi,</hi> which without any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive expence would have made it an admirable Structure, and very commodious for the Coaches, either when it rained or ſhined having changed this deſign, I ſay, he follows that of ſome Modern Architects, who have made it of an extraordinary greatneſs, for it is to be of a Circular form, with three Walks or Alleys, and all of Stone of <hi>Tivoli.</hi> And although the Architects have found by their Calculation, that the expence will not exceed five hundred thouſand Crowns; yet if we reckon accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to what the little that is finiſhed already hath coſt, we ſhall find, that what is proportionably to be done, cannot be completed hardly for a million of Crowns.</p>
            <p>Theſe high and great deſigns are very certain marks, that the Pope has a Soul truly Royal; and truly he makes it appear in all the publick actions he undertakes, as may be ſeen by the reception he made of the Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> in which he omitted nothing that might add any glory or luſtre to make it proud and equal, if it were poſſible, to the Ancient <hi>Roman</hi> Triumphs; and by his Magnificence he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited the whole Court to ſhew the complaiſance
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:135322:13"/> they take in following and imitating herein the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations of his Holineſs: But when we conſider on the one ſide, that the Apoſtolique Chamber is drained by the inſatiability of the preceding Popes, and on the other ſide, that the times are miſerable and had, the profuſion of ſo much Treaſure appears to the world to be ill husbandry and not in ſeaſon, ſince it might have been employ'd with more praiſe and merit, and to better purpoſe, for the moſt preſſing Neceſſities of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> who looking upon <hi>Rome</hi> as the North-Star to guide them, and the Pope as their Tutelary God, cannot but be afflicted to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him, inſtead of healing their wounds and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing their diſtractions, amuſing and pleaſing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in raiſing and adorning of ſtately Walls. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it cannot be denied, but ſuch great Spirits do extremely thirſt after Glory and Renown. The wiſeſt men, who perceived it from the beginning, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways ſcoffed at the Popes ſparingneſs in the firſt years of his Reign, as not being willing to ſee his neareſt kindred, much leſs inrich them: nay more, it was their opinion, that he affected this little glory of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing his particular Intereſts, thereby to acquire himſelf a greater afterwards, as if already he had the ambition to do thoſe things, which Popes of a moſt holy life could never do before: But ſince that the world has found the Pope extremely glad to be induced by the Cardinals and the Miniſters of other Princes, to call thoſe of his Family to <hi>Rome,</hi> while in ſo doing it might appear, that he was rather prompted to it by the earneſt intreaties of all the Court, than by the flatteries of his kindred. <hi>Rome</hi> is too ſubtle, and can dive too far into the deſigns of thoſe that command her not to perceive this, and how rigorouſly ſoever they forbid them from judging
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:135322:13"/> the actions of their Princes; yet would they not forbear it on this occaſion. And to ſay truth, they could not apprehend how the Pope, who hath ſo much ambition to revive the memory of his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, could ſuffer it to be buried in the oblivion of his kindred yet living; theſe were contradictions that could not in any wiſe be reconciled. But, however it were then, certain it is, that at preſent they are ſo well at their eaſe, that ſhould the Pope die, they will have no cauſe to envie others riches: anon I ſhall give the reaſons more particularly. But e're I go further, I will not omit to let you know the Original of this Houſe, and by what degrees the Pope could riſe to ſo high a Dignity.</p>
            <p>His Nobility is as conſiderable as could be in the City of <hi>Siena,</hi> where they are regiſtred in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of thoſe antient Families, that have been ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with ſuch Commands as that City is wont to beſtow upon her Members, and have maintained themſelves by their Alliance with thoſe Families that were nothing inferior to them. But this is not the firſt time that they have made themſelves known at <hi>Rome.</hi> In the time of <hi>Julius</hi> the Second the Houſe of the <hi>Chigi</hi> had employments in the Court, not of Prelature, but Offices in the Chamber, which ſpreads the names of thoſe that exerciſe them over all parts; and at that time the <hi>Chigi</hi> made theirs the more known, becauſe they hapned to ſerve a Pope both paſſionate and turbulent above all others. Whence follows, that becauſe of the profuſion of monies thoſe that are thus raſh are forced to make uſe of to maintain the Wars they undertake. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine Chigi,</hi> who managed the Treaſury, had a fair opportunity to play his part, being naturally active.
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135322:14"/> But though he were very ſtirring, and that there was much jealouſie about the adminiſtration, yet <hi>Julius</hi> never had the leaſt diſtruſt of his integrity, on the contrary he teſtifi'd the good opinion he had of him by thoſe marks of Honor he beſtowed, in ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pting both him and his Heirs into the Houſe of the <hi>Rovere,</hi> whoſe Arms they bear to this day.</p>
            <p>Since that, in the time of <hi>Paul</hi> III, (as great employments are expoſed to great dangers) thoſe of the Houſe of <hi>Chigi</hi> found themſelves eclipſed a little of their firſt ſplendor, which was cauſe that the beſt of their means being alienated, and eſpecially their delicious Garden on the <hi>Tyber,</hi> juſt oppoſite to the Palace of <hi>Farneſe,</hi> which remained to the Houſe that held the Chair, they returned to their Country, where in a moderate, but honorable condition, they quietly paſſed their time, till an opportunity offered it ſelf to <hi>Fabius Chigi,</hi> who is Pope at preſent, and who was then a young boy of great hopes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſtate himſelf in a better fortune, as he was encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged by his Parents and Friends, who believed, that a perſon adorned wich all manner of virtues would much wrong himſelf, ſhould he hide thoſe rich Talents, and let them lie buried in idleneſs, by not going out from the gates of his own City. But he was hindred by the little wealth he had, and alſo becauſe his friends had not been able to advance themſelves during the long interval that thoſe of his Family had been kept from the Court: Nevertheleſs, where power is wanting, his confidence in putting himſelf forward by what means ſoever ſhewed it ſelf. For being come to <hi>Rome,</hi> he got acquaintance of the Marquis <hi>Pallavicino,</hi> at that time a young man of great virtue, and for that cauſe ever very welcome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:135322:14"/> to <hi>Urbane.</hi> This is he, who ſince made himſelf a Jeſuite, and who having been promoted to a Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalſhip ſometime ſince, will oblige us to ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of him hereafter.</p>
            <p>This Marquis then brought him to the Pope's feet, and preſented him as a perſon capable to bring any buſineſs about with honour, when ever any oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion profer'd to ſerve the Holy Chair. His manner of deportment pleaſed the Pope, ſo that how mean ſoever his eſtabliſhment were at firſt, it was not long ere he was appointed to be Inquiſitor at <hi>Malta,</hi> in which employment he having made his worth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, was ſhortly after ſent in quality of Vice-Legate to <hi>Ferara.</hi> There it was, that what had been conceived of his virtue being made known, he was ſent Nuncio to <hi>Collen,</hi> in a time when the diviſions of Chriſtendome were at their heighth. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in this employment he did not ſucceed ſo well as to conclude the Peace, yet he performed his part and devoire admirably well. But becauſe the Proteſtant Forces prevailed, with whom he could have no communication, being Miniſter to the Pope, it was not ſufficient that he had induced the Catholiques to make a fair and juſt accommodation, whilſt the others ſtood ſtifly on their exceſſive pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, ſo that he could not act as it might have been hoped he would have done, had he been to Negotiate between two Parties of the ſame Religion: but what is wonderful, is that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> who were both tired and diſcontented, being brought to this paſs to make the beſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation they could, the firſt with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and the others with the <hi>French,</hi> not onely without any advantage, but even to the prejudice of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:135322:15"/> and the Nuncio having expreſſed a great deal of his diſpleaſure to both of them, he did it yet in ſuch a manner as left no ill impreſſion on either Party, but on the contrary they were much edified to find nothing but zeal in him, judging thereby that he was ſo much a better Miniſter to his Prince, by how much he diſapproved what they had reſolved to do, rather out of neceſſity than any good-will, onely to preſerve both themſelves and their Religion from greater danger.</p>
            <p>He behaved himſelf with the ſame prudence when he returned to <hi>Rome,</hi> for being called to the charge of firſt Secretary, though he ſucceeded the Cardinal <hi>Pancirolo,</hi> in whom Nature had aſſembled all the circumſpection and craft that could be deſired, and that he was to ſerve a Pope ſo difficult to be pleaſed, as <hi>Innocent</hi> was; yet did he carry things ſo well, as that Pope was fully ſatisfi'd in all matters that he negotiated; and above all things he ſhunn'd as a precipice medling with the intereſt of the Pope's Niece, who would have all the Miniſters to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſhe was both Lady and Miſtris of that Prelate; and the Pope had ſo great a conſideration for him, that being at the laſt extremity, where the heart ſpeaks more then the tongue, and where all diſſimulation is laid aſide, he recommended him as a man very worthy to ſucceed him in the Papacy; ſo that it was not without reaſon that your Lordſhips from that time conceived for the Cardinal <hi>Chigi,</hi> that good opinion that ever ſince they have had of him, and amongſt thoſe you recommended to the Lords Cardinals <hi>Bragadino, Vidman</hi> and <hi>Ottobuono,</hi> I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that he was the firſt named by thoſe that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented you in <hi>Germany,</hi> as having all thoſe merits requiſite to fill the vacant Chair: which alſo hath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:135322:15"/> very happily ſucceeded. And truly, if we conſider the good conduct of his life, the integrity of his manners, and his knowledge of the Intereſts of all States, which are all qualities that meet in the Pope's Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there is no cauſe you ſhould repent your wiſhing it, or your having laboured to raiſe him: but the miſchief is, that what goodneſs and integrity ſoever the Cardinals have, they no ſooner begin to taſte the ſweetneſs of being Maſters, and having no Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior but God, but they change their natures, and think themſelves no longer obliged to follow thoſe Maxims they ſaid were rooted in their Souls whilſt they were Cardinals.</p>
            <p>Who would believe that Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> having ſo great a capacity, whereby he can truly judge of the dangers Chriſtianity is in, ſhould have aſſiſted the <hi>Turk</hi> to advance and eſtabliſh an Arſenal in <hi>Candia</hi> of all his Forces, and that he ſhould have ſhewed himſelf every way ſo obſtinate, as he did, in refuſing thoſe benefits which might ſerve in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncture?</p>
            <p>Who would ever have thought, that a Cardinal, who, before his promotion to the Cardinalſhip, breathed nothing but zeal, and ſeemed to languiſh with ſorrow, to behold the miſerable eſtate that Chriſtendom was going to be plunged into by that obſtinate War between two of her greateſt Crowns, ſhould not, being raiſed to the Holy Chair, burn with the like ardor for a general peace?</p>
            <p>Who would have believed, that when the moſt eſſential matters were agreed upon for the healing of our preſent miſeries, he ſhould ſeek to quarrel
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:135322:16"/> for very ſlight reaſons, which have no other object, but either to amplifie his juriſdiction, or maintain his own Opinions and Sentiments? I ſhall hint at many of theſe changes in this diſcourſe, that your moſt ſerene Lordſhips may conſider, as they have ever done, what confidence they may put in the words and promiſes of theſe Cardinals before and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their Elevation to the Papacy, who becauſe they cannot at firſt gainſay, what they have ſo lately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared they would do, afterwards by degrees lay aſide all manner of reſpect during their Reign, and onely knit themſelves to what their own proper intereſts, or the ſuggeſtions of their flatterers inſpire them with. But, in the mean time, not to omit what I promiſed at the beginning to make known, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Pope's neareſt kindred; thoſe towards whom his Holineſs bears the greateſt affection, are the Lord <hi>Don Mario</hi> his Brother, who married a Gentlewoman of <hi>Siena</hi> of the Houſe <hi>de la Ciaja,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Flavio</hi> his Son, at this time Cardinal, and ſirnamed the Cardinal <hi>Padrone,</hi> that is to ſay, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. He hath a like, and perhaps a greater affection for the Lord <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> the Son of another Brother, who was named <hi>Auguſtin:</hi> and this was he who having two years ſince married the Prince <hi>Borgheſe</hi>'s Siſter, remained Head of the Family after the death of <hi>Don Mario.</hi> I think it therefore neceſſary to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all theſe to your moſt Serene Lordſhips, ſince, as I have already ſaid, the divers accidents that hapned, did not permit your Miniſters to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late any thing to you of certainty.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Don Mario,</hi> who is five years elder then the Pope, is beloved of his Holineſs, as much as the tie and relation of kindred between them, and the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135322:16"/> reſpect he hath ever had for him does require, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out having, however received any other favour: becauſe the ſaid Lord <hi>Don Mario</hi> having for the moſt part had but a mean fortune, could not aſſiſt him, being young, any otherwiſe than by wiſhing he might arrive to that grandeur, and by preſaging his felicity, the little wealth that came to his ſhare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing allotted to other uſes. And as he nothing at all reſembles the Pope in viſage, ſo likewiſe are their manners and genius very different The one is lean, and the other is fat: the one is great, and the other little: the one is ſlow and mild, and the other is prompt and ſevere: the one is addicted to ſtudy and learning, the other never applies himſelf to it: the the one is of a high ſpirit, and ever undertaking great things, the other burns with covetouſneſs, and pleaſes himſelf with nothing but in ſeeking out the means to amaſs much Treaſure: And becauſe the Pope hath a good opinion of his integrity, he hath given him the Government of <hi>Rome,</hi> in what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the means to maintain abundance or plenty, and to content the people. But inſtead of that, there is nothing elſe heard over all the City but complaints againſt his Miniſters or Officers, who buy and ingroſs before the ſeaſon, to retail and ſell it to advantage, and who have other Monopolies, not onely of Profits, which none till his time had ever thought on or practis'd, but likewiſe all thoſe which cuſtome had allowed under other Popes, whoſe neareſt kindred ever manag'd them. In the preſent Government there is this beſides, that they do what they can to improve the Offices more than ordinary, which are us'd to belong to the Pope's kindred, by ſuch ways and ſubtilties as were never heretofore made trial of.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:135322:17"/>
            <p>In the Government of <hi>Borgo,</hi> where the Lord <hi>Don Mario</hi> exerciſing his juriſdiction, makes that of Governor of <hi>Rome</hi> to ceaſe with a notable augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Profits of his Tribunal, he makes uſe of ſo much rigour, that every day one hears nothing but lamentations, and by his inexorableneſs to ſhew favour, he makes the preſent Government to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more and more odious. It hath ſeldome hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to me to have had any affairs with his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, becauſe it belongs not to his Office to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with any matters which the Pope treats of with other Princes, unleſs he have an expreſs Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet did I not omit to wait upon him at thoſe times we are wont to renew our complements; and I ever brought away particular aſſurances of the great eſteem he hath for your moſt ſerene Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips.</p>
            <p>The Lady <hi>Berenice</hi> his Wife, although ſhe were born in a City where they ſeldome live after the Court faſhion, hath ſo admirably faſhion'd her ſelf to it in the ſhort time ſhe lived at <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſhe is able at preſent to teach others: which we muſt not wonder at, ſince whatever ſhe ſpeaks is naturally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compani'd with ſuch a certain kind of modeſty and affability, as gains the affection and attracts the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of all thoſe that converſe with her. She may be about 48 years of age. She is rarely admitted to the Pope's preſence; nor does ſhe ſeek very much to crave his favour, it being ſo enjoyned her at her firſt appearance in <hi>Rome,</hi> that ſo by her abſtaining to intermeddle in things not concerning her, the Court might perceive how odious it was for the Niece of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> to delight in the management of all affairs; wherein he that ſuffered it was much more blameable than her ſelf.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:135322:17"/>
            <p>The Cardinal <hi>Flavio Chigi,</hi> is a young man of 29 years, of a mean heighth, black hair'd, and his viſage round and fat, of a conſtitution mixt betwixt a San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine &amp; Melanchollique. He would enjoy his health more perfectly were he but moderate in his diet, wherein he exceeds: for he eats much, &amp; very nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing meats, without regarding the precepts given him for the preſervation of his health. It is ſaid likewiſe, that he's not ſo moderate as he ought to be in his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the fleſh, which obliges him oftner than might be expected from his youth, to keep his bed: but the Phyſitians, becauſe the Cardinal forbids them, do not tell the Pope the true reaſons of his confinement, for fear his Holineſs ſhould have an ill opinion of him, and look upon him as a debauche', that loves both Wine and Women too much. I cannot affirm any thing with certainty of his ability in affairs, becauſe if he be able to do no more than he does, I muſt ſay, that he can do but little, ſince one gets no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from him but complements, fair excuſes, or promiſes, which in the end turn to nothing, making all his anſwers ſpeak either of the repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance he met with in his Holineſs, or ſome other motive, that was occaſion of the refuſal, or delay of an Affair. And for this reaſon, I thought it far better in any thing of importance to go my ſelf directly to the Pope, than to make uſe of the interceſſion of the Cardinal, who being for the moſt part diverted by his Paſtimes, either forgets ſome of thoſe circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances which are very eſſential to a buſineſs, which might make the ſucceſs the more eaſie, or elſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſces with the firſt denial, or difficulty the Pope makes in it; and this brings afterwards a double trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, firſt to inform him quite anew, and then to take off ſome prejudice or miſconſtruction it may before have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:135322:18"/> left on his ſpirit. I have been forc'd to ſteer the ſame courſe, when I hapned to have any Petition to preſent, to obtain the proviſions of ſome benefits for any ſuch perſon as had deſerved well, either of the State or the Embaſſie it ſelf, becauſe if I reli'd upon the promiſe of the Cardinal, I commonly found my ſelf deceived. He would ſend me back to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Dater</hi> that Signs ſuch Writings, aſſuring me, that the Pope referred himſelf wholly in matters of Collation of Benefices to him. So that perceiving it was pure weakneſs of judgment it proceeded from, or the little care he took to do me any courteſie, I never afterwards made any great account of his mediation; when I had occaſion to treat of any thing that required diſpatch: becauſe this Cardinal, who is called the Maſter, does exerciſe his Maſterſhip more in ſpending his time merily, and avoiding the moſt he can all troubleſome affairs that diſturb his mind, than in rendring himſelf conſiderable, as he might be, in an employment that gives him the greateſt authority. This Cardinal does not ſhow any great deſire of heaping up riches, becauſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, having no Nephews iſſued from Brothers, and finding his Branch ends in him, he little cares to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire much Treaſure to enrich the Deſcendants of his Couſin <hi>Don Auguſtin,</hi> on whom otherwiſe all the advantages that Fortune can beſtow on a Man, will fall. In things indifferent this Cardinal hath ever treated me very civilly, and hath ſhewed me a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular affection; and truly I believe, if he had but more courage to undergo the part he acts, by his means, one might receive greater favours of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, than thoſe which now come from him ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily but by little and little. He ſhows, that he is vers'd in our Hiſtory, for he relates from time to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135322:18"/> time our happy ſucceſs, and he ſays freely, that <hi>Italy</hi> would be very unhappy, had ſhe not had this <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique</hi> for a Bulwark, which hath bounded the ambition of Strangers, and repelled the rage and incroachments of Barbarians. When I took leave of his Excellence, I could not deſire greater expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of his affection than thoſe he uſed, accompany<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them with proteſtations, that he would paſs the bounds his Holineſs had preſcribed him, to give all kind of ſatisfaction to your Excellencies in the matters then in hand. Theſe are his own words, <hi>It is not reaſonable that the diſcontent for particular affairs ſhould cauſe a prejudice to that which concerns the General, which is, to maintain the Grandeur of that State inſeparable with the ſplendor of</hi> Italy.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Don Mario</hi> hath no other Son than this Cardinal, but he hath beſides two Daughters, married at <hi>Siena</hi> in noble Families, that have but moderate Fortunes, proportionate to the condition of the Family of the <hi>Chigi,</hi> in the time they were married: and theſe are they that ſhowed themſelves not long ſince at <hi>Rome,</hi> where they were exceeding well receiv'd and carreſs'd by their Father and their Mother, and the Cardinal <hi>Chigi;</hi> but they were not received with ſo many tokens of affection by <hi>Don Auguſtin,</hi> for the reaſons that I ſhall declare. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not certainly tell, whether they obtained a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency from the Pope to maintain them in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition they are in, becauſe things were carried with a great deal of circumſpection in not making known what was done, for fear the Court ſhould think that the Pope waſted the Demeſns of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> to put his kindreds Wives in a handſome condition; and for fear likewiſe of giving ſome cauſe of jealouſie to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135322:19"/> 
               <hi>Don Auguſtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who expecting hereafter to be Chief of the Family, could not but with trouble behold ſo many others, that were not of the Pope's Maſculine Line, thus gratifi'd or enrich'd: It is certain how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, that the Lord <hi>Don Mario</hi> and his Wife, did not let them return empty handed, but gave them a ſhare of what they had ſtored up, and do endeavour to encreaſe with ſo much Art and Induſtry.</p>
            <p>But let us proceed to the other Branch deſcended, as I ſaid, from <hi>Auguſtin Chigi,</hi> which conſiſts of two Lords, <hi>Don Auguſtin</hi> and <hi>Sigiſmond.</hi> As for the firſt, who may be about 24 years of age, he is naturally merry, very pleaſing and amiable. He never appli'd himſelf at all to ſtudy, but in thoſe Exerciſes as befits a Gentleman. He loves to paſs his time as well as any man, and cares very little to heap up any thing, becauſe he knows there are thoſe that do it for him. As ſoon as ever he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> they thought of providing a Wife for him, and caſt their eyes upon the beſt Match in the whole Court, to wit, the Grand-daughter of the Prince <hi>Mark Antony Borgheſe.</hi> But they could not bring it to paſs with that facility they imagin'd, becauſe the Prince, being a man that was very wary, eſpecially when it concerned the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of his Family, ſcoffed at the Propoſition, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>That he ſhould take that Alliance for a very great honor, but firſt deſired to ſee</hi> Don Auguſtin <hi>have grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wealth and dignity, that ſo his Granchild might at leaſt be able to keep a rank ſuitable to her quality and merits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe excuſes the Prince made were not very pleaſing to the Pope, who at the firſt word would have had him made more account of his Alliance
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135322:19"/> than any other conſideration whatſoever. For this cauſe the buſineſs hung a long while in ſuſpence, but ſtill with repeated applications of Love and Courtſhip from the Lord <hi>Don Auguſtin,</hi> who follow'd it with the more heat, as having the Conſtable <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonnes</hi> for his Rival, a young man of moſt excellent qualities, and towards whom the Princeſs ſeemed to have a greater inclination than for himſelf. But the Prince <hi>Borgheſe</hi>'s death hapning thereupon, and the Tutelage falling to the Princeſs her Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, in a few days, by the mediation of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Roſſano</hi> her mother, this Match was concluded, conſiderable for her great Dowry, which was one hundred and fourſcore thouſand Crowns, beſides what might hereafter fall to her by ſucceſſion, the Houſe of the <hi>Borgheſes</hi> having but one more Heir, a young Lord of a ſomewhat melanchollique conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, who nevertheleſs about the ſame time, out of divers good conſiderations, would needs wed ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther young Lady, having more regard to her Beauty and Virtue, than her Riches. <hi>Don Auguſtin,</hi> as well as his Holineſs, thought, by the contrivance of this Match, which was celebrated with all the Pomp imaginable, that they had eſtabliſhed the happineſs of their Family on the beſt foundation that could be; In effect, the Lady being an extraordinary Beauty, and brought up under the Diſcipline of her Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mother, a very Religious perſon, there could be nothing more deſired upon that account; and he hath already begun to taſte the fruits of it, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs having given him the marks of her fertility by the birth of a young Daughter ſhe hath brought him. This does not, however, hinder <hi>Don Auguſtin</hi> from diverting himſelf elſewhere according as his temper and fancy leads him, and his great inclination to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135322:20"/> pleaſure, when it comes in his thoughts. This ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of all content making him forget his firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, hath ſo puff'd him up with pride, that he ſeems to take no notice of thoſe who paſſing by ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute him in the ſtreets: which likewiſe makes him not ſo much beloved as his other fairer qualities deſerve. Nay, it is not long ſince he made ſhew of the little reſpect or regard he had for perſons of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; for having taken ſome diſtaſte at the pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing or ſitting of the Conſtable <hi>Colonnes,</hi> he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the Cavalier <hi>de la Ciaja</hi> his Uncle to do a very diſobliging act, by thruſting the Conſtable out of his place at a Comedy, whereat the <hi>Colonnes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing offended, the Pope was extreme angry, and would have it taken up by any means whatever; as it was afterwards done, but in the name of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier, who was but an inſtrument in that action: but this inſulting left a great deal of diſcontent on the ſpirits of the <hi>Colonnes</hi> againſt <hi>Don Auguſtin,</hi> who was the principal author of it.</p>
            <p>A while after his Nuptials, he purchaſed in the Province of the Patrimony, for ſeventy thouſand Crowns, the Principality of <hi>Farneſe,</hi> which is ſaid to be a Fief of the Empire of four thouſand Crowns Revenue. He hath alſo purchaſed a conſiderable Palace for his Family: but beſides theſe, he pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſes little, living at vaſt expences, but upon hopes that the Pope's long life will furniſh him with ways enough to enrich and raiſe his Family to as brave a heighth as the greateſt of the preceding Popes.</p>
            <p>I have had divers occaſions to ſpeak with him of his Marriage and other affairs; and he hath ever given me teſtimony of a great eſteem and particular
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135322:20"/> affection, which proceeded, as he told me, from the Pope's good-will, from whom I truly never heard any thing, but what was much in praiſe of this Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene <hi>Republique.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have obſerved likewiſe, that the Princeſs his Wife, though ſhe were but a Novice in the way of treating the Miniſters of Princes, hath now informed her ſelf ſo far, as to let them know what ſatisfaction ſhe receives by the devoirs they render her, and how much ſhe is obliged to their civility.</p>
            <p>It remains now to ſpeak of <hi>Don Sigiſmond,</hi> who arrived at <hi>Rome</hi> but a few weeks before my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. He is a Youth of twelve years of age, and ſeems to have much of his Brother's way, and, foraſmuch as can be noted in him at preſent, is very fair con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition'd, and of ſo much judgment, as promiſes he will in time prove ſomewhat. As ſoon as ever he came, the Pope delighted to reaſon with him ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, thereby to diſcover his vivacity; and was ever well ſatisfi'd. <hi>Don Auguſtine</hi> will do all he can to have him made Cardinal. But if the Pope fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows his own Maxims, he ſhould not favour him therein, having affirmed it a horrid thing to behold ſuch Under-Branches in the Sacred Colledge. However, we may believe there is nothing but he may do, ſince he hath already begun to exceed all that he at firſt propounded to have done. In the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim, this little Nephew hath already ſeveral Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and if the Pope ſurvive his Infancy, it may then be eaſier to obtain a Cardinals Hat for him.</p>
            <p>There are two Nephews by the Pope's Siſter, who married into the Family of the <hi>Bichi;</hi> the one
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135322:21"/> is he that was made Cardinal at the laſt promotion with the Father <hi>Sforza Pallavicino,</hi> and the other is the Prior, who having reſided ſomewhile near your Excellencies, in quality of Receiver for the Religion of <hi>Malta,</hi> and having likewiſe been three times with the Squadron of the Popes Gallies at <hi>Candia,</hi> in quality of Lieutenant General, hath made himſelf fully acquainted to your Excellencies As touching the firſt, I have no great matter to ſay of him, for having not been long at <hi>Rome,</hi> I could not perfectly know him: It is ſaid, however, that he would have been a better Biſhop than a Cardinal; for he hath made it appear that he can govern a Church well, which is that of <hi>Oſime,</hi> where he is Prelate, but he hath not yet ſhown that he hath the Talent to go thorough any great affairs; nor did I trouble my ſelf with any further information. I did reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence him as I ought, when occaſion profer'd to complement him, and I alſo took my leave of him at parting, very well ſatisfi'd with the manner of his reception, and the ſentiments he hath for this Republique.</p>
            <p>But as for the Prior, whom common Fame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends as a man of great merits, he never made me ſo happy as to know wherein that Virtue conſiſts, ſince it is reſtrained within a perfect obedience to thoſe that can do him good, or raiſe him to ſome degrees higher than he yet ſtands; for he is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to make ſuch profound reverences to the Pope's Nephews, that the loweſt of their ſervants would not perhaps do the like. But as for his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in commanding at Sea, and taking his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages either to attaque, or hotly purſue an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, or in diſtributing the publick Treaſure ordained
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135322:21"/> to that end, I ſhall not need to waſte time in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating it to your Excellencies, ſince it was your ſelves informed me how little benefit had been reaped by the Popes Galleys in theſe parts, when commanded by this Cavalier. It is certain, that the laſt year there was a great deal of Treaſure put into his hands, and it is as certain by the accounts that have been calculated without his knowledge, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have expended the one half. But there are none ſo confident as to advertize the Pope of theſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors, becauſe he having ſo good an opinion of him, would think it all to be onely ſpleene and envy that could be alledged againſt him: and therefore you commanded me very prudently to abſtain from all complaints, for fear of withdrawing the Pope's good will and forwardneſs in purſuing the ſuccour you demanded of him, which, though it were not diſpiſeable, became ſo notwithſtanding, by a not exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting of the Pope's true intentions therein. Which made me (though the Cardinal <hi>Chigi</hi> perceived ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of theſe miſcarriages, to whom I might have opened my ſelf with much freedom and aſſurance, and neither Pope nor Prior ſhould have known what I ſaid, that Cardinal having ſo little inclination for him) obey your Lordſhips moſt punctually in what you commanded. But the common complaints hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not been kept ſo cloſe, but they came to that Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal's ear; he one day, perhaps to oblige me to ſpeak, told me, <hi>That he admired that the Prior, who ſo much deſired to gain honor and renown, had not made ſome enterprize of himſelf, ſince he found it unfit to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake any joyntly with others:</hi> But lifting up my ſhoulders, I onely ſaid, <hi>That it might be, the bad for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of the Republique hindred ſuch men, though very skilful in the Art of War, and valiant, from ſhowing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:135322:22"/> any marks of their great courage;</hi> The Cardinal per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving he could get nothing elſe out of me, ſaid ſmiling, <hi>That the Prior had had the good luck to be prized more than he diſerved, but yet was unhappy in not being able to maintain that good opinion had been conceived of him.</hi> The two Branches of the Houſe of the <hi>Chigi,</hi> who otherwiſe do not agree very well, united together to hinder his being made a Cardinal, and it ſeemed to them they had done much in ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining their ends herein, they judging the Prior to be a man of a great wit, and one who, as ſoon as he could have had the power to have ſpoken freely, would have made a diviſion in their Houſe; they have more acquaintance with him than my ſelf, and by conſequence may know him better. As for my own part, I never could find any eminent virtue in him, nor do I believe, he deſerves to riſe to any great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, to which he pretends to mount by his diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling humour.</p>
            <p>There is not among ſo few kindred as have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and who are in a direct line, ſo great concord as there ought to be, and this proceeds from a vain ſpirit which makes every one of them aſpire to rule. The Lord <hi>D. Mario</hi> pretended, that he, as the moſt antient, and next to him, his Son at this time a Cardinal, ought to be head of the Family, and that by right it belonged to him to encreaſe their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber by marriage. But the Pope, who had a greater affection for his diſceaſed Brother, than for him that is living, was of another mind, and from hence aroſe the ill-will that hath ſtill encreaſed amongſt them. The Pope never did any good to any of <hi>D. Mario</hi>'s Family, but <hi>D. Auguſtin</hi> interpreted it partiality. He ſaid, It appeared to Cardinal <hi>Chigi</hi> but a ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135322:22"/> to have the quality of Patron, and the ſupreme Superintendence of the greateſt affairs, unleſs they allowed him together with this the Authority of granting all Acts of Grace as he pleaſed. He added, That it was little benefit to him to be the Son of a Father, who with his purſe had raiſed the Pope to that heighth of honor, if now, whilſt he was in poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, he might not receive the profits and rewards deſerved for his Father's former readineſs and libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality. What will become, ſaid he, of the heaps of of mony <hi>D. Mario</hi> gathers up, unleſs to enrich the Houſes of Strangers? meaning his Daughters who were married at <hi>Siena,</hi> leaving thoſe naked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>furniſhed which are of the blood of the <hi>Chigi,</hi> who ought ſtill to abound in goods and riches. To which the Cardinal <hi>Chigi</hi> repli'd, That the Authority and Superintendence they had given him ſtood him in no ſtead, but to trouble his brain, for which he had a very great averſion, whereas they had left to the other the enjoyment of all the delights and applauſe of the Court: That <hi>D. Auguſtin</hi> taſted more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in the freedom he lived in, being diſingag'd of the management of all publick affairs, than himſelf could meet with amidſt all that power and authority they had inveſted him withall: And thus neither of them, becauſe of theſe contentious pretences, which though but whiſpered, are apparent and known to all, do enjoy that entire ſatisfaction they might, were their minds but united, and they contented with thoſe degrees of eminent Dignities which Fortune hath lifted them too. The Pope knows nothing of all this, they fearing very much to give him any cauſe of diſpleaſure; and from this conſideration his Holineſs does ſometimes confer favours upon the one, ſometimes upon the other, thereby to keep
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:135322:23"/> them from all kinde of jealouſie. He permitted <hi>D. Mario</hi> to let his Daughters and their Husbands come to <hi>Rome,</hi> and would have them there attended and ſerved as became thoſe of his own blood. He conſented that <hi>D. Auguſtin</hi> ſhould ſend for his little Brother to abide with him; but neither of them will remain contented when their Authority ceaſes, which diſquiets them far more than a neceſſary ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude would do.</p>
            <p>The Pope hath now at <hi>Siena,</hi> as I have already ſaid, many others of his kindred, who are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered much as yet, becauſe they are of more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote degrees. They may, after the others are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently inriched, hope for ſome good from his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, if he continue long alive, he being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally much inclined to favour thoſe of his own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, by employments proportionate to the abilities of his fellow-Citizens: there are already ſome that have principal Offices at Court, who are deſign'd for Cardinals, and there are other places reſerved for others, when an occaſion preſents: To which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be ſaid, but the Pope deſerves a great deal of praiſe, in that he forgets not to do well for his own Country, to which, next to God, we owe our ſelves; and in that he does not imitate the pride of ſuch, who being once abſent looſe the very remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of it, and never take the leaſt care for any one that had a being there.</p>
            <p>But foraſmuch as the Miniſtry of the Pope's kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſerves onely for ſplendor and ſtate, and not in any thing eſſential; and that in preſſing and weighty affairs it is requiſite he be fortifi'd with the aſſiſtance of ſuch as have a clear inſight into the management
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135322:23"/> of great Negotiations, from whom, upon occaſion, prudent and ſolid councel may be taken. I have eſteem'd it fit to joyn, to the Pourtraict I have made of his Holineſs kindred, a Character of thoſe who are made uſe of, in the moſt important intereſts of the Popedome, and ſuch on whoſe will depends moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the reſolution of what is of the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence.</p>
            <p>THe firſt that preſents, is the Cardinal <hi>Roſpiglioſi,</hi> born at <hi>Piſtioſe,</hi> who is Secretary of State; One cannot ſpeak ſo well of him, but he will deſerve more, nor can I think there could be found a man worthier of that Office, and the Pope, who knows him well, hath often ſaid, that he had found a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary according to his own heart. He hath a great deal of judgment, and is ſincere and diſingag'd from all intereſts; He is not obſtinate in his opinions; when he hath deliver'd them, he takes pleaſure in having them moderated and cenſured; according as the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Maſter does require; He is indifferent in his ſentiments, and although it be the common be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, that having been Nuncio in <hi>Spain,</hi> where he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came extremely beloved of the King and Court, he might bias that way, and cheriſh ſome inclinations for the advantage of that Crown; yet it is falſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in my time there were ſome troubles in that Court, which might have been appeaſed by the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of a Miniſter ſo much in credit; but the more they believed he took the <hi>Spaniards</hi> part, the more he abſtained from medling with their intereſts. He did all he was able not to give audience, not deſiring any other employment than his own charge, to
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135322:24"/> which he applies himſelf with all the exactneſs poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, carrying every night to his Holineſs all his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs digeſted, and taking himſelf the pains to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Letters, which relate to any intereſt that may be any way conſiderable. I can ſay, that he never ſeemed to be diſpleaſed or unwilling to hear me ſpeak; But it is true, that I had a care never to demand audience of him, but in preſſing and earneſt occaſions, and always had the ſatisfaction that could be expected from a Miniſter, obliged to ſwerve the leaſt that poſſibly could be from the will of his Prince. Now this ought to be the more conſidered, becauſe if the Holy Chair ſhould happen to become vacant at this time, I eſteem his hopes very well grounded, having the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the Great Duke on his ſide, and probably too the Heads of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions that would predominate in the Conclave, that is to ſay, <hi>Barberino,</hi> who in <hi>Urban</hi>'s time firſt moved the wheel of his fortune, and <hi>Chigi</hi> who cheriſhes him moſt, as being his Creature.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is the Cardinal <hi>Pallavicino,</hi> of whom the Popes make great eſteem, as well for the reaſons I pointed out before, as becauſe of the very good opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he hath of him, holding it for certain, that he would never give him any counſel, which were not good and advantagious for the Church. To tell the truth, he is a man that hath very good intentions, and knows much, but he fails in what all thoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily do, that have devoted themſelves to a ſolitary life, and who profeſs a different way of living from thoſe of the world, being extremely obſtinate in their opinions. I have diſcourſed with him on ſeveral oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, even when he was a Jeſuit: and although for the intereſt of his order, which is now received
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135322:24"/> into the favour of your moſt ſerene Republique, he ſeemed extremely deſirous to do me ſome pleaſure, yet I never could truly obtain any thing from him. He hath a thouſand excuſes to defeat one of thoſe good offices he might do. Since he was made a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, though it were expected one might hope for ſomewhat more, yet I have found him ſtanding upon his guard more than ever, pleading the pretence of ſome command the Pope had laid on him not to intermeddle in any affair that were not agreeable to him. In a word, I am not ſatisfi'd with him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he often mention the deſerts of his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors from this Republique, and the obligations, which thoſe of his Order do in particular owe unto him. The Pope refers much to him in matters of <hi>Theology</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and confers with him, too, about thoſe of <hi>State,</hi> but rather to know than to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his advice, becauſe moſt times he looks upon things according to the rigour of the Eccleſiaſtical Laws. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ambaſſadour was not very well pleaſed with him, who when all the other Cardinals had been to viſit his Wife, he would not, upon a pretence, that although he had changed the habit of his Order, yet he hath not changed the Rules, which prohibits them to be amongſt Women but in caſes of great neceſſity. This kind of behaviour, which is an affected ſingularity, renders him odious to a great many people. He did not oblige your Lordſhips, when he put forth his Hiſtory in anſwer of the Book of the deceaſed <hi>Padre Paul</hi> of the Order of Servants, wherein ſpeaking too freely of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter whom you have ſo much cheriſhed, he gave you cauſe to oppoſe him, as you did at the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Hiſtory, of which having ſaid ſomething to me by way of excuſe, I preſently ſhifted the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135322:25"/> that I might not obliged to enter upon ſuch tetchy ſubjects, upon which if we had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, he might have alledged many Metaphyſical diſtinctions, which it is not my profeſſion to anſwer; but had he treated of that buſineſs in a way more ſuitable to that ſubject, I am confident I ſhould have been too hard for him, and put him at a ſtand.</p>
            <p>In divers things the Pope makes uſe of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Corrado,</hi> a <hi>Ferrarian,</hi> and principally in thoſe differences which Secular Princes have concerning Eccleſiaſtical matters, wherein his Holineſs is but ill ſerved, for that Cardinal is a pure Legiſt. that hath no knowledge in the affairs of the world, who alleages a deciſive Text on any matter in queſtion, without any regard to the decency or reſpect is to be had towards a State, or any moderate inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation where required; for he never makes any account of this certain Maxim, <hi>Summum jus ſumma injuria.</hi> This man hath, and does continually give diſtaſte to the Cardinals and other Miniſters of Princes, becauſe he keeps himſelf ſtill to the rigour of the Canons, and will diſtribute the Benefices ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own fancy, and always upon pretence that it is the Pope's will, which he turns as himſelf pleaſes under a fair appearance of Sanctity. But the diſguſts he practiſes, and is accuſtomed to put upon all the world, does more hurt to himſelf than to any one elſe, for having been ſo unadviſed as to diſcover his baſe humor, it hath drawn the hatred of all upon him: So that for the Chair there is nothing to be expected on his part. I never had but little ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from him. And indeed, ſince I began to know his defects, I never took the pains to do him any courteſie that might acquire his favour, thoſe kind
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135322:25"/> of perſons thinking they do in ſome manner ſacrifice themſelves, whenſoever they do but in the leaſt act againſt their own opinions to a man a little pleaſure.</p>
            <p>I muſt alſo bring into this number <hi>Signior Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinelli,</hi> of <hi>Siena</hi> great Maſter of the Apoſtolique Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, an old Courtier, refined in the Great Duke's Court, from whence the Pope called him, and took him to his own ſervice, knowing the noble manner of his acting. He is not a man of a very profound knowledge, but of great experience; which makes the Pope take great delight in conferring with him, who is ordinarily well ſatisfi'd with his advice. Amongſt other qualities that makes him conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, there is one that is a very particular, which is, that he is deſcended from <hi>Alexander</hi> III, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been forced to flie, and quit his ordinary abode, made his retreat in this Republique, who received him in their boſome, and gave him their protection, which he made uſe of to repreſs the audaciouſneſs of the Emperor <hi>Frederick,</hi> that perſecuted him. He glories more in this, than in any thing beſides, and hath a particular veneration for the merits of your Serene Lordſhips. There is no one more certain of a Cardinal's Hat than he. It is due ro him, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving quitted his own Country, where he was very much in favour, to go to <hi>Rome.</hi> When he hath a Cardinal's Hat, the whole Court, who already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he deſerves the ſupremeſt degree, will be ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh'd for joy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Signior Fagnano,</hi> of the State of <hi>Urbin,</hi> a Prelate well known at Court for his being blind, but much more for being ſo clear ſighted in the Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:135322:26"/> which the Pope hath given him over the affairs of the Regulars, deſerves that I ſhould make mention of him in this Treatiſe, becauſe thorow his means, I have ſometimes made an end of a difficult buſineſs, which otherwiſe I ſhould ſcarce have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. This Prelate hath a great deal of affection for this Serene Republique, as having been the firſt that found out the invention to draw mony from the ſuppreſſion of the unprofitable Religious Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, as alſo from the Scandalous; ſo is he likewiſe ſtill of opinion, that ſince the ſame neceſſity ſtill remains, they ſhould make uſe of the ſame means of ſupply, there being poſſibility and reaſon enough to continue it. But that deſign having been inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by certain zealous perſons, upon ſome other pretexts which they found out; he endeavoured to ſeek out ſome other projects to aſſiſt your Serene Lordſhips therein. And truly he might have found out ſomething effectual, did they as well ſee the dangers at <hi>Rome,</hi> as they do in theſe places that are ſo near bordering unto it. However, I did not omit to give this Prelate many thanks for his great good-will, and I believe it will be very fit that you ſhould return him thanks likewiſe: I think alſo, that his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency <hi>Sagredi,</hi> who carries ſeveral Curioſities to preſent to the Pope's Family, ſhould beſtow ſome part of them on this good man, who hath, and may yet render upon all occaſions, all thoſe good Offices which can be expected from the confidence his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs puts in his advice, and the great credit he gives him.</p>
            <p>The Father <hi>Virgilio Spada,</hi> one of the Order of the Congregation of St. <hi>Philip Neri,</hi> and Brother to the old Cardinal <hi>Spada,</hi> hath ſome power with the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135322:26"/> Pope; and upon this perſwaſion I have ſometimes endeavoured to get him to ſerve me upon occaſion, but I found him armed with a thouſand excuſes to evade doing me any good: whereat I did not after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards very much wonder, knowing he onely ſought the advantage of his Family, being very greedy after his own intereſt, and more ready to put the Pope in mind of filling his own purſe, than ſeeking any largeſs for others: This made me forbear to ſolicite him, gueſſing the little profit that was like to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound, to make trial of other ways which your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips are not unacquainted withal, although they all proved fruitleſs, and too weak, when it concerned his Holineſs to disburſe any monies, which is not kept cloſer in his own Coffers, than it is by all the Court Prelates, who think to gain credit and repute from his Holineſs, by exhorting him to preſerve that Metall, which above all things makes the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Principality be highly eſteem'd, as if it were not rather the Dignity and Sanctity of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prieſthood that render'd the Papacy Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, than the reputation of having great riches, But we need not doubt but their abuſes being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived to the heighth we find them, the Eccleſiaſtick Authority would be very weak and languiſhing, were it not ſuſtained by a Temporal Power; whereas if thoſe Prieſts would lay aſide their vanity of agran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing themſelves, and onely make good their juſt degrees and privilege, the Church would ſoon be lifted above all other Powers whatſoever. For to ſay truth, Whoſoever beholds the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing in Magnificence and State, the Courts of all other Princes, cannot but wonder by what means, upon ſo ſlender a foundation, and ſo far from the deſign and intentions of her firſt Founders, ſhe ſhould
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135322:27"/> have raiſed her ſelf to ſo proud a heighth. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though every one knows it proceeded from the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berality and Magnificency of Temporal Princes, yet it cannot but appear ſtrange to ſee the <hi>Roman</hi> Church turn thoſe Benefits, ſhe hath received from them, againſt themſelves to their prejudice; the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts and other Emiſſaries of that Court ſtudying nothing more, than how to ſtrengthen and extend their Eccleſiaſtical juriſdiction, and abaſe and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the Secular, if they poſſibly could. This point, wherewith you have been ſo often enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd, deſerves yet ſtill to be put into your memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, becauſe without any diving into the depths of a profound Speculation, it may be obſerved, that conſidering the by-ways the Popes do tread, and withal reflecting on the ſincere conduct of Secular Princes, of neceſſity it muſt follow, that the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Monarchy will become Miſtris of the World, and the Secular fall and become her Servant. Your Serene Signiory hath a great deal of Piety, and a particular Veneration for that Holy and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique Tribunal; who likewiſe hath a ſingular good-will towards her: but yet ſhe knows well how far ſhe ought to ſhow her veneration; and herein ſhe carries her ſelf prudently, being very well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſed of thoſe things which do inſenſibly lead the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> to enlarge her Phylacteries more and more: And this Note ſhall ſuffice by the way.</p>
            <p>And ſince we are now upon the diſcourſe of the Grandeur of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> it will not be amiſs to ſhow what it is, becauſe as it appears great by looking onely upon thoſe things which makes the Courts and Dwellings of other Princes conſiderable, yielding, in effect, neither for number of Miniſters
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:135322:27"/> or Officers to none in Chriſtendome, it will ſeem yet far greater, by having for Aſſeſſors and Counſellors ſeventy Kings, for they give that Title to the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals in the Act of their Creations; and therefore it is that they are veſted in Purple, and are ſerved almoſt like Kings: and when together with this Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity they have acquired a great Reputation, their Amity is ſought by the moſt puiſſant Princes, who by publick or private Penſions endeavour to make them their friends, becauſe of the privilege they have of Electing a Pope, and what by conſequence muſt follow thereupon, the Soveraign Dignity lights upon one of themſelves; and this is in ſhort the cauſe of all their arrogancy, which otherwiſe is often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to contempt enough, beſides the vexation of not being able to obtain any grace, unleſs they be the Pope's Favourits. It may be expected that a Pope, who hath ſo excellent a judgment to diſcern how thoſe perſons ought to be qualifi'd that are fit to be aggregated in that Sacred Colledge, as Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> hath, ſhould promote none but perſons worthy of his choice: and, indeed, the Court hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto hath no reaſon to complain, ſince he hath ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted none but ſuch as deſerved very much, and it is hoped it will be ſo ſtill for the future. Now, though it would be needful to make an exact ſearch and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the quality of the preſent Cardinals to know them thorowly; yet that your Lordſhips may have ſome knowledge of him; that ſhall one day be raiſed to the Chair, I ſhall make no difficulty to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it; and I ſhall acquit my ſelf with much bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, becauſe there are many other things to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined, which your Serene Lordſhips will be glad to know.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:135322:28"/>
            <p>The Cardinal <hi>Charls de Medices,</hi> Uncle to the Great Duke of <hi>Toſcany,</hi> is the Dean of the Sacred College. He never ſhows himſelf at <hi>Rome</hi> but when the Chair is vacant, he takes more pleaſure at his own home, being free both from clamour and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence. He leads the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Faction, not without a great deal of hopes from the Great Duke, who long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for nothing more than to have a Pope that may favour him, becauſe of the troubles and traverſes the Popes put him to, who little conſider him. He was not at the Court whilſt I was there. But the oblige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humor of that Prince is not unknown to your Lordſhips by other means, as likewiſe the great joy he ever expreſſes at the leaſt news of your proſperity. He is a man that ſpeaks little, hath a good wit, and ardently deſires the advantages of his Family: to ſerve whom he rather ſuffer'd a long while in the Conclave, then gave way to elect any perſon that might not be pleaſing to the Great Duke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Francis Barberino,</hi> who in the time of <hi>Urban</hi> and his Domination made ſome eſcapes, being hurri'd thereto rather by the impetuoſity of his nature, than out of any evil intent, perceives at preſent that it is in vain to trouble the world, having extremely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd himſelf by diſcovering the violence of his paſſions. He hath loſt all his hopes of ever attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſit in the Holy Chair, which his Uncle <hi>Urban</hi> held, though otherwiſe both for his knowledge, and the candour of his mind, he is worthy to be placed therein. Which evidently ſhows, that innocency of life is no ſufficient motive to oblige the Cardinals to chuſe a Man for Pope, it hapning very often, that together with the greateſt Sanctity there may be joyned ſome other ſuch defects, as were able to put
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135322:28"/> the whole world in a confuſion. Nevertheleſs <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berino</hi> hath a little recover'd his credit under <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> they having noted the inconveniencies hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in that Popes manner of Government, which they alſo found in <hi>Urban</hi>'s time; but with more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Although his Family inclines towards the <hi>French,</hi> yet he hath ever ſhewed that he hath more regard for the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> his humor ſuiting better with the Genius of that Nation. As for the affection he hath for your Serene Republique, I cannot ſpeak ſo fully of it, but I ſhall leave ſomewhat untold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spada de Breſighele,</hi> which is a place in <hi>Romagnia,</hi> is a man more conſiderable for his Virtues than his Birth, and who for this reaſon deſerves more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe than he yet hath. But it ſeems they do not look upon him with ſo good an eye becauſe of the proſperity of his Family, who are lately in poſſeſſion of much riches, which ſome of the oldeſt amongſt them have acquired by their Farms and Marriages; and which have alſo been ſince multiplied thorow the induſtry of this ſame Cardinal, and the Father <hi>Virgilio Spada</hi> his Brother, who hath not been want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſtriving to acquire wealth, and raiſe his Houſe, though he make profeſſion of a retired life. This Cardinal hath many very good qualities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, which make him worthy of a higher degree? but that which hinders him from riſing, is the envy many have againſt him, and the great number of Nepveus he hath, which are like to be encreaſed by thoſe Marriages they have of late contracted. I muſt add to this the little confidence the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have in him, who think him a very ſubtile man, and one that hath a great inclination towards the <hi>French.</hi> He hath a high eſteem for this Republique, and hath as
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135322:29"/> much reſentment in all her troubles and dangers as any one whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sachetti,</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> hath entred Pope twice into the paſt Conclaves, but ſtill came forth again Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, to the great regret of good people, and ſuch as are acquainted with his virtues. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> did not murmur ſo much againſt his elevation, as the <hi>Florentines,</hi> who endeavoured all they could to thwart his Election, and I believe it now proceeds from no other cauſe, but onely they having been once engaged to exclude him, imagine that he will for ever reſent the injury they had done him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he may have ſerved them much ſince. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, there are few in the Colledge ſo worthy, if we conſider all his good qualities. He hath made himſelf the more fully known, by that conſtancy wherewith he hath undergone thoſe diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the ſollicitations he made to <hi>Mazarine,</hi> to lay aſide all thoſe jealouſies which might make him oppoſe the exaltation of the Cardinal <hi>Chigi,</hi> whom he eſteemed more worthy of the Chair than any other, in a time wherein his own hopes were not deſperate. He keeps the ſame reputation ſtill at Court which he had formerly, and if his advanced age would let him ſurvive the preſent Pope, he would ever have the ſame applauſe as formerly. He is commonly very indifferent in his affection to other Nations, ſeldome favouring one more than another; but I dare confidently ſay, that he is partial for your Republique.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ginetti</hi> of <hi>Veletre</hi> is a Cardinal, who though he be rich, and have a great deal of experience, yet does nothing that gains much commendations, or
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:135322:29"/> that makes him eſteemed worthy to be raiſed higher than he now is. There is no other reaſon than the poorneſs of his ſpirit appearing in all his actions, and his inſatiable deſire to enrich himſelf; whence they draw this conſequence, that ſhould he be mounted higher, few ſhould partake of his Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deurs or Bounty; add hereto, that having been one of <hi>Urban</hi>'s greateſt Confidents and Creatures, he is entirely poſſeſſed with thoſe Maxims which are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing convenient for the good of Chriſtendome. He omitted nothing his power to make himſelf Pope the laſt times the Chair was vacant, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he found ſome Cardinals his friends, who liſtned to him in hopes of partaking of his favours, yet he found no body for him amongſt the Princes, who cannot promiſe much good to themſelves from a perſon ſo wedded to his own intereſts, and ſo little inclined to favour others. I know not, indeed, what to ſay of him. He makes profeſſion of much devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but I ſhould hardly ever truſt a man, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his other defects, hath the reputation of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly knowing how to diſſemble.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal <hi>Antonio Barberino</hi> is a man, who all his life time hath ever been even gentility and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity it ſelf. He is engaged as much as can be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to <hi>France,</hi> but in ſuch a manner however, that he does not make himſelf odious to other rival Nations, becauſe he ſpeaks of all the world with a huge deal of reſpect; and brings his affairs ſo about, that none can juſtly complain of him. He reaps many ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages from the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs does not make him the richer, but rather the contrary, ſince he conſumes more money for them than he receives, as well in entertaining his friends
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:135322:30"/> perpetually whilſt he is in <hi>France,</hi> as in advancing the intereſts of that Crown. And by reaſon of the great inclination he hath for that Country, where they live according to his humor after a very free manner, he would rather make his reſidence there than in any part of the world; but it is obſerved, that <hi>Mazarin</hi> does not look on him with a good eye, perhaps out of jealouſie, becauſe his carriage, which is ſo fair and pleaſing, might be a diſadvantage to him, while he is more than any man alive in favour with his King. He was the firſt who, at the publica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Peace, manifeſted the good-will he hath for <hi>France,</hi> and that in ſuch a noble and ſplendid manner as was thought worthy of his generoſity. The affection he bears that Nation does not make him, however, forgetful of what is due to the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> and particularly to your Serene Lordſhips, whoſe merits he never mentions but with admiration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Colonne,</hi> a <hi>German,</hi> is the Head of his Family, by the diſpoſal of the deceaſed <hi>Don Philip Colonne</hi> his Father, who having cleared his debts by his good husbandry, thought fit to recommend the direction thereof to that Son who ſeemed to be moſt wary and ſparing: Nor was he deceived in his choice, ſince this man, conſidering his riches, which are great, eſpecially if we reckon what he hath from the Church, is ſo reſerved, when any mony is to go from him, that is preſumed, during the long time he hath managed their Eſtate, he hath heaped up a very great quantity, taking much delight in hoarding up continually, but never expending any thing in a ſuperfluous manner. To which the Suits he oppoſed by Law, which the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135322:30"/> of that State had for a long time maintained till his Fathers death, have not a little contributed, who thinking themſelves moſt unjuſtly deprived of thoſe Honours pretended to by his Family, diſputed it very obſtinately againſt him, but in the end yielded up all his antient prerogatives to him, which much augmented his Revenues, and hath gained him a very great eſteem. At that time when his Holineſs exhorted all thoſe that were rich, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute ſomewhat towards the aſſiſtance of your moſt Serene Republique, he was the onely Cardinal that excuſed himſelf, alleaging the dammage which the Plague had done him in his Eſtate: Nay, it hath been propounded to him onely by way of trial, to give out Mony at the higheſt Intereſt, as your moſt Serene Republique is wont to allow, but all was in vain; although he ſeems to glory his affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, by which profeſſion he thinks he hath fully compleated his devoire.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Franciotti</hi> of <hi>Luca</hi> is an honeſt man, and of ſome underſtanding in moſt affairs; but theſe kind of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt people do not ſucceed ſo well when they have the Government in hand They take a licence in all extravagant opinions, and become obſtinate and punctilious, not caring how they trouble the world, provided they can but maintain their own fancies. This man imagines that he ſhould behave himſelf well enough were he in command, although he ſhow himſelf but of a mean ability in ordinary matters. He was born in a Republique, and the Prelateſhip of his Country lighting on him, he ſoon put them in a condition of falling out with him, yea, and of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting and quarreling with the Pope too, and that for very ſlight reaſons. In the end, all theſe <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villeries
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135322:31"/> ve diſputes</hi> having conſtrained him to quit his Church, he left his Family involved in ſuch trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles as have much perplexed, and brought many great loſſes upon him. To repair this, he lives in hopes of being Pope, but he expects it in vain, for I do not know any one that deſires it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Brancaccio,</hi> a <hi>Neapolitan,</hi> though he were made a Cardinal when he thought not of it, and, as it were, by an unexpected accident, does not for all this omit any poſſible endeavour to mount higher: He is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> to whoſe ſhame he at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained that Dignity: He hath made a ſtrict Amity with the Great Duke, and is on good terms with <hi>Barberino:</hi> in a word, he does all he can to make good, and increaſe his credit, which is as yet but ſmall, becauſe his thoughts ſoar too high. Some have ſaid, that there was nothing reſting but a good un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding with the <hi>French,</hi> but that being equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, I ſhall take it in the beſt ſenſe, from whence one may infer, that he treats with them in ſuch a manner as may diſpoſe them not to be againſt him, if he ſhould happen to be mention'd. He ſeemed to me to be paſſionate for you, nor ſhall I believe he diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled much therein, having wit enough to know what your moſt Serene Republique hath done for the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Harach</hi> of <hi>Behemia</hi> comes to <hi>Rome</hi> onely when the Chair is vacant: There are few other things can oblige him to ſtay there, all his intereſt depending on the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and the Imperial Court. And being a Cavalier of a very frank Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, he makes it appear, that the arts and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation, uſed ordinarily in the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> are
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135322:31"/> not pleaſing to him. He hath ever teſtifi'd a great deal of affection for your moſt Serene Republique, for ought that ever I could learn from thoſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded me in my employment; but having never been at Court in my time, I cannot tell what judgment I ſhould have made of him, had I been acquainted with him my ſelf.</p>
            <p>I cannot affirm any thing of the Cardinal <hi>Palotta</hi> of the <hi>Marcha:</hi> thoſe reports which I have heard of him being very various: Some have told me that he hath ſtrange fancies, which being paliated with the zeal of Reformation, cannot but cauſe a great deal of trouble and diſorder. Others deſcribe him to be a very honeſt man, of a good conſcience; yet all this is the ſame onely diverſifi'd, becauſe the reſolutions of theſe kind of ſpirits, or their whimſeys rather, do ſtill claſh themſelves: And therefore he was very little lookt upon in the laſt Conclave, where he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed as much as poſſible his deſire of being Pope, yet could he not carry it ſo cloſe but his Confidents diſcovered the extreme paſſion he had for it. The Pope makes no great account of him, although he have had ſome Legation: and there is ſome likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of reaſon for it; becauſe thoſe that are lifted to the dignity of Pope, can better judge of the defects of their inferiours, than ſuch as are their equals in authority or degree. In his Legation of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> he gave ſome occaſion of conteſt to your Signiory, and therefore although he ſpake much of her commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, I ſhould never confide in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carpegna,</hi> of the State of <hi>Urbin,</hi> had reaſon enough to hope in the laſt Conclave, becauſe the Great Duke and <hi>Barberino</hi> did not reject him, nor are his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135322:32"/> qualities to be deſpiſed. But, in a word, when a Cardinal wants a certain credit which is given by popular approbation, he ſeldome ever attains to the Chair It cannot be denied, but that both probity and ſimplicity of manners do meet together in this Man. He underſtands and can do as much as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the managing of publick affairs, but as for the preſſing of them on, or, if I may ſo ſay, the refining of them, he is not much applauded for being happy therein: nor during the laſt Conclave was there any one that could promiſe himſelf more than very mean reſolutions for the publick ſervice, under his Government: and therefore as ſoon as ever he was ſpoken of, they found that he had not a ſpirit great enough for ſo high a dignity. Nevertheleſs he ſhewed himſelf worthy of praiſe, in that whatever his hopes, and the reſolutions of the Conclave were, he never ſeemed to trouble himſelf. He loves your moſt Serene Signiory well enough, which I have gather'd from the diſcourſes he hath held with me, as alſo from the reports of ſuch as have heard him in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular converſations, when mention hath been made of publick affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Filormarini</hi> of <hi>Naples</hi> hath made known his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in thoſe diſputes he had with the King's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, during the laſt troubles in that Kingdome. He ſhew'd an invincible courage upon the threats which were like to have ſucceeded to effects of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt him, to make him quit that Country. But he likewiſe ſhewed a very great humility towards the Catholique King, thereby to let him know, that he was diſturbed wrongfully; and his plea herein carried it againſt all that the greateſt Miniſters of that Crown could oppoſe againſt him. But by how
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:135322:32"/> much he hath encreaſed his reputation thereby, ſo much hath he alſo therein prejudic'd himſelf, as to the thoughts he might have had of hopes and greater dignity, thorow that obſtinacy apparent in him not to change, or remit any thing of his firſt reſolutions, how dangerous and violent ſoever the attempts are againſt him. He was a confident ſervant of <hi>Barberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi>'s in the time of his proſperity, whoſe ſervices have been very well rewarded. But I do not know what thanks thoſe can promiſe to themſelves that ſhould help him to be made Pope, he being a man that hath a marvelous good opinion of himſelf, and one that believes every thing is due to his own merits. I never treated with him, he not having been at <hi>Rome</hi> in my time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maculano,</hi> or St. <hi>Clement,</hi> a <hi>Dominican,</hi> is a ſmall Brother, who under his poor mean Frock huggs am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious and high thoughts. He builds fine Caſtles in the aire, fancying, that as he came to be a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal without meriting of it, ſo he may as well riſe to the Pope's Chair. There is no quality to be found in him that can diſtinguiſh him from the vulgar. He hath little or no experience in State-affairs. He is learned as a Monk, but excells not their ordinary capacity, and hath ſome skill in Fortifications: But with this he is very covetous: and loves his Nepveus exceedingly, who are young people of very ill behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours: if he had the command, which God forbid, there would be matter enough of ſcandal. This was taken notice of, by him that could have aſſiſted him, to wit, <hi>Barberino,</hi> who hating a licentious life, would never ſpeak one word for him, though <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culano</hi> had friends to ſecond what he ſhould have ſaid, and were aged enough to pretend to the Place.
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135322:33"/> Nevertheleſs he may live very well at his eaſe, if he will content himſelf with the condition he is in poſſeſſion of, which truly ought to ſatisfie him. He hath named himſelf for Candidate, which is to ſay, he aſpires to the Chair, though amongſt thoſe of his own Fraternity, he could never have attained to be General of their Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Giorio de Camerino,</hi> a ſervant to the Houſe of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berino</hi> in buſineſs of ſmall conſequence, found a way by his handſome manner of ſerving, to gain ſo much upon the good-will of his Nepveus, and afterwards on Pope <hi>Urban,</hi> that having gotten much riches in his long ſervice, he was reputed worthy to be a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal. He is very little eſteem'd at Court, his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour not being noble enough to correſpond with his dignity. He keeps cloſely united to <hi>Barberino</hi> his Soveraign Benefactor, and in that ſhews he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to be advanced. He hath never been nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated for to be made Pope, nor is there any great hopes he ſhould be in election, becauſe, beſides the meanneſs of his birth, thoſe qualities are wanting in him which ſhould make him worthy to ſtand in the rank of ſuch as pretend to that Supreme Dignity, unleſs they ſhould puſh him forward purpoſely to make him fall, and get time in the interim to nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate another's preferment with more ſecurity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Facchinetti,</hi> of <hi>Bologna,</hi> hath been employed in the higheſt Offices of the Court, and Nunciator of <hi>Spain,</hi> with a conſtant reputation of an honeſt man, and very able. This is a Cardinal, of whoſe repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation they have very advantagious opinions, which when time ſuits will make them willingly reflect on his good qualities; and this fair opinion they have
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135322:33"/> of him he preſerves, by making his ordinary reſidence at his Church of <hi>Spoleta;</hi> and avoiding all occaſions that might forfeit it, by not concerning himſelf with the preſent Court intereſts, for fear leſt in medling therein, inſtead of increaſing his reputation, he ſhould give ſome cauſe of diſguſt and rupture; He is a Lord of a very ſweet converſation, and ſpeaks paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately for the intereſts of your Signiory, from whom I dare promiſe effects coreſpondant ſhould he attain to a higher degree.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Roſetti</hi> of <hi>Ferrara</hi> is a creature born, bred, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd in the boſome of <hi>Barberino,</hi> who loved him by accident, and after helped him to employments, which raiſed him up to be a Cardinal. He was in danger being in <hi>England</hi> during thoſe troubles, which have encreaſed ſo long as to arrive to the ſtrange heighth of misfortune they were then in: But a more wary Miniſter might have withdrawn himſelf without forfeiting his devoir. Being at <hi>Collen</hi> in quality of a Nuncio, he could not avoid being ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of partiality towards the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and did together with them, breed ſome diſorder in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs. At <hi>Rome</hi> he did not ſhew himſelf very grateful to his Benefactor, having ſubjected himſelf to the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> In the Conclave he was almoſt the onely man that diſapproved the Election of the preſent Pope. So that all theſe things being heaped to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, one may infer, that he is not a Cardinal of any eminent vertue, although he hath been wiſe enough to make ſuch good uſe of his time, as to have freed his Family from thoſe inconveniences which attend a mean Fortune. He keeps himſelf at his Church at <hi>Faenſe,</hi> without any deſign of ſhewing himſelf much at <hi>Rome,</hi> where till thoſe evill im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135322:34"/> are taken off, or forgotten, he would not be looked upon with any great good-will:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grimaldi,</hi> a <hi>Genoeſe,</hi> ſhews by his looks, that he is a man of great undertakings, from whom no other effects can be expected, but ſuch as uſually proceed from penſive ſpirits, which are quarels, jealouſies, bold and daring enterpriſes, with all kind of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilties to make good his deſigns. This man hath had ſome great deſigns on foot already, to the prejudice of the publick peace, and that onely for ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to himſelf, without regarding the incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience of others: and this was the cauſe, that finding he was mounted as high as he could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, which was to have a good Church in <hi>France,</hi> where he might ſay, <hi>Here is my reſt;</hi> imagining that he ſhould be a ſecond <hi>Mazarin,</hi> he was deceived, <hi>Mazarin</hi> deſiring to reign alone, that the world might know they owed the good ſucceſs of that Government to his direction. He was not at <hi>Rome</hi> in my time; thoſe that were acquainted with him have deſcribed him to me, to be as crafty a man as any one, but yet a perſon wanting that addreſs or diſcretion, which like Salt ought to ſeaſon all the parts of Policy. I ſhould not confide in his words, when he commends this State, becauſe we ought not to give belief to ſuch men, as propound no other end but their own intereſt.</p>
            <p>Here I ſhould ſpeak of <hi>Mazarin,</hi> and there might be much ſaid of him, but your moſt Serene Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips are ſo well informed of the Perſon and Maxims of this great Miniſter, that I could ſay nothing which would not fall ſhort of the knowledge you have elſe-where had of him; yet ſhall I not omit to let
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135322:34"/> you be acquainted in what eſteem he is with the preſent Pope; which I believe is a thing worthy your knowledge, becauſe you may from thence gueſs the true reaſon of the difficulties in thoſe affairs which muſt neceſſarily be treated of in either Court.</p>
            <p>The Pope had very ill impreſſions of the Cardinal when he was Nuncio at <hi>Collen,</hi> for obſerving atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively the reaſons the Mediators alledged for a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Peace, he found the <hi>French</hi> had always ſome reſervations in their anſwers, which did not corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpond, as he judged, with the equity of the <hi>Spaniards</hi> propoſitions; which made him fully perſwaded, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on ſome other inconveniencies hapning when they came to confer, that all the obſtacles which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded ſo great a happineſs for all Chriſtendome; proceeded from the Cardinal <hi>Mazarin.</hi> But, as the ends he then propounded requir'd him not to diſcover his opinions therein to thoſe Nations that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſs'd, ſo he negotiated ſtill with ſo much caution, that few or none knew what was in his thoughts. Being returned afterwards to <hi>Rome,</hi> and the place of Secretary of State being given to him, he was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifi'd more than ever in the ill opinion he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived againſt the Cardinal, being thereto induc'd, not onely by an increaſe of the difficulties in the Treaty on the <hi>French</hi> ſide, but likewiſe by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious ſpeeches of Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> who had a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular averſion for <hi>Mazarin,</hi> and who always blamed him as the onely cauſe of the dammage and ruine which Chriſtendome ſuffer'd under. Which made <hi>Alexander,</hi> being raiſed to the Papal dignity, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had ſome reaſon to forget his hatred, ſince <hi>Mazarin</hi> condeſcended to his Exaltation) to become more envenom'd, becauſe amidſt the hopes he had, that his mediation might produce ſome good
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135322:35"/> towards a General Peace, he underſtood, that the ways leading thereto were more blockt up than ever, <hi>France</hi> being Leaged with <hi>England</hi> without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the intereſts of the lawful Succeſſors of that Kingdom, or any conſideration that they were of the Blood-Royal of <hi>France,</hi> not minding, as the Pope ſaid, the Reputation of the moſt <hi>Chriſtian King,</hi> which by this baſe alliance was even trod under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot; whence followed, that laying aſide all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration he had till then ſhewed in ſpeaking of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarin,</hi> one could not ſo much as mention the affairs of <hi>France,</hi> or thoſe that treated of them, but his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs would flie out to ſtinging injurious expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, diſcovering what he had with much art con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed ſo long before; <hi>That he took him to be the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſpring of all the miſeries in Chriſtendom, That in him alone had the Heretiques founded all their hopes to predominate over the Catholiques, And that there was a juſt cauſe to apprehend, that from him would ariſe a general diſturbance againſt the publique Peace: That this doubly diſpleaſed him, becauſe of the wrong he did to that Dignity which he unworthily ſuſtained; And though his Predeceſſors had not conſidered the ſhame that reflected on the Sacred College, in ſuffering this man to be the firſt Author of all thoſe miſchiefs, he hoped that God would give him both courage and power enough to reſent, as he intended, the prejudice that was thereby done to Religion, and the advantages the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies thereof had procured.</hi> If ſome body, under the pretence of ſeconding the Popes Reſentment at that time, had not by a diſcourſe ſuitable to his humor, endeavoured powerfully to moderate his paſſion, it is to be feared he would have proceeded to ſome greater violence and anger: But he that heard the Pope's complaints made a very prudent uſe of them, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135322:35"/> to wipe all thoſe evil opinions of him out off his thoughts and memory. As for my own part, though at the beginning of my Embaſſie, I found the wound yet open, I omitted not, on every occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, when I thought it convenient, to inſinuate to his Holineſs, that theſe times oft required, that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons ſhould in their counſel overſway Princes, and that it was an effect of great prudence to lay aſide all bitterneſs when we treated with them, unleſs we would have that wound, which perhaps would heal up of it ſelf, to become incurable by often rubbing of it: that he might have his reaſons likewiſe, which being heard, would juſtifie or, perhaps, expoſe him leſs to cenſure for ſuch reſolutions, which ſometimes do not depend on his will alone, but the reſult and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of other Miniſters, with whom his Maxims would not ſuffer him to diſagree. And if it were otherwiſe, yet however, <hi>France</hi> did not enjoy ſo great a happineſs as to deſire a War, unleſs it were appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that thoſe who counſelled it had very powerful motives to continue it, till they could find out a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain way to make both a good and laſting peace. Theſe reaſons ſufficed to moderate the Pope's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints a little, yet was he not ſo well ſatisfi'd, but rejecting him he ſaid, <hi>That when ever he had a mind to obtain any thing of his King and Council, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned his particular favour or intereſt, he knew how to obtain what ever he fanci'd, it being known to all to what a height and grandeur he had by his ſubtilties raiſed his Family, and thoſe that had joyned their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts with him; but, when ever it was required that he ſhould act for the good of the Publique, his power was weak and languiſhing; which was a very clear argument, that he ſaw the augmentation of his fortune depended on a continuance of the War, which afforded
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135322:36"/> him a thouſand opportunities to make new friends and creatures by the diſtribution of Offices, which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed, according to his own will, upon ſuch perſons as gave him much applauſe, which he preferred, though it laſted but a moment, to the immortal glory he might have acquired, by delivering Chriſtendome from ſo great and continual troubles, as put it in danger of being at laſt made the prey of</hi> Heretiques <hi>and</hi> Mahometans. In the mean while, the times of Audience appointed, were waſted in theſe and the like Diſcourſes, which troubled me exceedingly, becauſe I foreſaw, that from this Antipathy, which daily encreaſed, we could not but expect ſome great and notable prejudice would accrue to the Publique.</p>
            <p>After this, upon the firſt ſlight rumors, which were whiſpered of the Peace, the Pope ſuſpected it was ſome new artifice of <hi>Mazarin</hi>'s to lull the world aſleep, and take off his hatred againſt him, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to renew the War afterwards, when during the Truce he had juſtifi'd his pretences; but having been certainly informed that the Peace went roundly forward, and that things were brought to ſuch a paſs, that none could doubt of a good ſucceſs from this Treaty; then he declared both to me and all others that he was highly pleaſed; but every one knew this content of his was mixt with an allay of diſſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to ſee that <hi>Mazarin</hi> had made himſelf the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrator of Peace and War by this act, and attributed to himſelf alone the honour of doing both the one and other. I ſhall reſerve what I have to ſay here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, till I come to treat of that Chapter which ſhall treat of the Intelligence betwixt the Pope and <hi>France.</hi> But all the averſion the Pope made appear againſt <hi>Mazarin,</hi> did not take off the Court from admiring the capacity of ſo great a Man, who if he
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135322:36"/> truly did embrace more than the natural heat of <hi>France</hi> could well have digeſted (and in that reſpect ſome of his deſigns cannot be excuſed of temerity) yet it is obſervable, that Fortune hath ever been his Second, who fighting for him, he can never be want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of means to overcome the greateſt difficulties; For the world hath taken notice, that thoſe Parties he hath ſided with have rarely miſcarri'd, which makes divers confeſs, That how great a States-man ſoever the Cardinal of <hi>Richelieu</hi> was, yet he never had ſo much skill and policy in diſcovering and countermining the deſigns of Strangers, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing whatever he deſign'd to paſs, for the advantage of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> as this Man who was his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and Succeſſor; who if he ſucceed as well in times of Peace as he hath done in time of War, his name will be ſo much the more immortal.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Urſin,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> is of a Family known to your moſt Serene Lordſhips, as for the Services which his Grand-fathers have done for your State, which hath ever held them in great conſideration. They are, however, a little declined from their former Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, by the miſgovernment of ſome of the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of thoſe, who by their brave actions had raiſed it. That which hath cauſed no ſmall dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nution to their Honour, was, their bargaining for more or leſs with thoſe who made uſe of them to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade the liberties of others; to which may be added, that the number of their Family is diminiſhed. The Cardinal of whom we ſpeak, is more addicted to his pleaſures than to any ſerious buſineſs, which makes ſome deſire he had that ripe and ſtaid judgment which ſhone ſo in his Anceſtors. The Family does however but begin to recover it ſelf, at a ſeaſon
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135322:37"/> wherein it may happen to come to its period for want of iſſue; for having taken Wives rather rich than fruitful, out of a deſire to repair their loſſes, they are in a way of loſing their name by an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight greater than the former. They all make pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of continuing ſtill in the good affection they have ſo long preſerved towards your moſt Serene Republique. But they are worth little, and can do leſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eſte,</hi> Uncle to the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> hath made the world ſpeak of him, both in Peace and War. I cannot tell whether he were much pleaſed to ſee me at <hi>Rome,</hi> by reaſon of the little ſatisfaction his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had of me, whilſt I was Commiſſary for your moſt Serene Republique, at the beginning of the War you had with the <hi>Barberino</hi>'s. Although he can diſſemble, and is well enough skilled in the Art of concealing his reſentments, yet cannot I believe him ſatisfi'd with what I did, though the thing went not on ſo far as thoſe of the Houſe of <hi>Eſte</hi> pretended for their intereſt. The Pope, who hath not been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well ſatisfi'd with the Duke, who ſtudi'd to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the will of <hi>Mazarin</hi> in every thing, as if he had been his ſlave, and perceived that this Cardinal is of the ſame inclination, looks upon him as a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon more inclined to trouble than quietneſs; which he does not however divulge, becauſe he hath grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pretences than ever to that portion of Eſtate which was not annexed to the Dutchy of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> when it fell to the Church, as I ſhall ſhow in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place. It will be difficult for him therefore to be looked on favourably by the Pope, who hath made it appear, that he can right himſelf by the Sword, when they deny him Juſtice. This Cardinal
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135322:37"/> keeps a Palace at <hi>Rome,</hi> where there are much Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Nobility, that are punctually paid: which evinces, that the late Wars hath impoveriſhed the Subjects, and very much enriched the Maſter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Coſtaguti,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> but born of a <hi>Genoan</hi> Father, is one of that ſort of men that can eaſily heap up wealth, by which they have raiſed this Houſe to its Nobility and Purple; but to judge of their fortune, as we are wont to judge of all new begun proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities, one may ſay, That ſo great riches acquired in ſo ſhort a ſpace of time, are hardly compatible with any lawful means of obtaining them. But not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, the Cardinal is a very agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man, and he did hugely ſatisfie me, in ſhowing me he was ſo well informed of the intereſts of this State, and had ſo full a knowledge of the merits of your moſt Serene Republique.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Donghi,</hi> a pure <hi>Genoeſe,</hi> came forth of <hi>Genoa,</hi> when he was not expected, with a very conſiderable ſtock of riches, which hath ſince opened the way to his greatneſs; having been much furthered by thoſe qualities he hath, which are ſo deſerving, that he that raiſed him hath no cauſe to repent the doing it. The Court does generally praiſe him: But he was ever abſent all my time, ſo that I can give no judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of him, but from the reports of others, which however do tend to allow him the quality of a Man of merits, and one that is very affectionate to your moſt Serene Republique.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rondanini,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> though he be originary of <hi>Romagnia,</hi> is worthy of the degree he ſtands in for the goodneſs and ſimplicity of his manners. But he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:135322:38"/> is otherwiſe no great man, for he hath but a weak judgment, which would eaſily loſe it ſelf ſhould he apply himſelf to buſineſs. He deſerves, however, the good-will of your moſt Serene Signiory, for the many things he ſpeaks in her praiſe, and for the many Services his Family hath done your State, whereof the blood of the Marquis his Brother was a teſtimony, who would needs ſignallize himſelf in an Employment as worthy as a War for Religion and Liberty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gabrieli,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> is a man that endeavours to conceal what is in his heart; for inſtead of diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering himſelf, he makes a great Apology of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements. There are ſome of opinion, that his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice may help to raiſe him higher, but I do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, becauſe the manner of acting of Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent,</hi> which is that of the <hi>Romanes,</hi> hath opened the eyes of the world too much, the preſent times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring rather a perſon that will prefer the publique good than his own. He abides the moſt part of his time at his Church of <hi>Aſcoli,</hi> feeding himſelf with this Maxim, That the leſs a Cardinal is at Court, the eaſier is it for him to get into the Pope's Chair. But, though that may be true in general, yet it holds no water amongſt the cunning and refined <hi>Roman</hi> Wits, who by this very retreat diſcover his mind ſooneſt that would thereby hide it, and who ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that Man firſt, who is moſt skilful in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of great affairs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lugo,</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and Jeſuit, is a man very learned in Divinity, but ſince he forſook the Pulpit he hath ſhewed himſelf no leſs skilful in State mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. He acted with great ſucceſs in the Conclave
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135322:38"/> for the election of the preſent Pope, and though <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berino</hi> were cried down for deſiring to make him Pope, out of a certain fancy that came in his head, yet did he uſe his utmoſt endeavour to advance <hi>Chigi,</hi> whom he knew to be very favourable to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, as he hath ſince ſhewed himſelf. He can do no more than he now doth to make it appear to your Signory, that he hath a great eſteem for you, and that he is extremely troubled to ſee her op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by ſuch fierce and potent Arms. I believe he ſpeaks frankly, being a conſciencious man; but perhaps, too, the great deſire he hath to make thoſe of his Order more acceptable amongſt you, prompts his tongue to ſay more than is in his heart.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Raggi,</hi> a <hi>Genoeſe,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Raggi</hi> his Uncle, was made a Cardinal by the <hi>Genoeſes</hi> means, who to raiſe him to this Dignity expended twice as much as is uſual. But it is very juſt that the mony, which they ſqueeze from all the world, ſhould be afterwards turned into that ſmoak which the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> daily ſells. This Cardinals endowments are very proper and fit for a Miniſter of the Chamber, as he hath been a long time: and indeed, there are few that do ſucceed better in that employment than the <hi>Genoeſes,</hi> who are moſt active in running about to fill their purſes. I am told, that ſince he is made Cardinal, he hath ſhewed himſelf ſomewhat more gallant, and hath pretty well ſtudied the affairs of the world, which may be ſoon learned having a very preſent wit, if he do but apply himſelf as much to it, as he did in his Office of the Pope's Treaſurer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Homodei,</hi> a <hi>Milanois,</hi> choſe rather to follow the Prelacy, and attain to the Purple, than to preſerve
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135322:39"/> his Family, which is in hazard of periſhing for want of Iſſue. It is nevertheleſs conſiderable, full of wealth, and alli'd to the greateſt Families in <hi>Spain.</hi> He hath obtained what he pretended to, after he had made himſelf known to be a man capable of every thing, tying himſelf ſtrictly to the things that belong to his profeſſion. He is of a very free diſpoſition, as the <hi>Lombards</hi> generally are, ſo that one may confide in him. He let ſomething fall in the Conclave which did not pleaſe the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> but there were ſeveral in the Conſpiration, ſo that they could not lay the fault on him ſingly. He ſays plainly that he is a <hi>Venetian,</hi> as much as his fidelity to his King will ſuffer him, which is to ſay in good <hi>Engliſh,</hi> he is a good <hi>Italian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince <hi>John Charls</hi> of <hi>Medices,</hi> Brother of the Great Duke, is ever inſeparably united with the Cardinal <hi>Charls</hi> his Uncle, the Dean of the College; in this, however, his reputation is the greater, as having carried himſelf with much heat to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, and with much skill to the incluſion of thoſe, who being either partial, or his friends, were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded There can be nothing expected from this Lord, who is perfect in Reaſons of State, but ſuch actions as ſhall be favourable, and for the good of <hi>Italy,</hi> wherein likewiſe the good of his own Family is compriſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ludoviſio,</hi> of <hi>Bologna,</hi> who was grafted into that Family by the Mother of the Prince <hi>Ludoviſio,</hi> hath the reputation of an honeſt man, but he hath thoſe defects to which all ſuch kind of men are ſubject; for they are obſtinate and indiſcreet, and ſometimes too they have a grain of folly. It is difficult to Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiate
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:135322:39"/> with him, for if in any buſineſs it come once into his mind, that there is ſome caſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in it, it makes him ſo obſtinate, that nothing is ever able to make him change his opinion, and that moſt commonly without any reaſon, as the Officers of the Penitentiaries themſelves have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, of whom he is the Chief: Whence it follows, that although as a Soveraign Miniſter he might diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch buſineſs, ſeeing he hath the power, yet one muſt neceſſarily return to the Pope, and be at a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble trouble to obtain his command for the expedition of it. I dealt the leaſt with him I poſſibly could, it being hard to come fairly off with ſuch men, on the contrary, there is nothing to be gained moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly from them but ill-will and diſcontent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sancta Croce,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> agreed with Pope <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi>'s genius, in the eaſie and clear method wherein I have heard him expreſs the moſt difficult and knotty affairs, and that was it which gained him the favour of <hi>Innocent:</hi> for although that Pope were a great Lawyer, yet he did not very readily underſtand a difficult caſe; and therefore he loved thoſe that made things out eaſie and clear to him, and fit for his apprehenſion: beſides, he had taken a fancy to raiſe the ſomewhat depreſſed antient noble Families of the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobility, as was this of <hi>Sancta Cro e,</hi> that they might owe the obligation to him. He had accompliſhed this deſign, had not his Niece with her much importunity diverted it. It is certain, that the incluſion of this Cardinal was highly praiſed, he having added both Virtue and Merit to his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, which good opinion he confirms by the daily proofs he gives of his good-will in all publick affairs.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:135322:40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Cibo,</hi> who is one of the Lords of <hi>Malta</hi> of <hi>Carrara,</hi> hath a great reputation at Court, becauſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity of his mind, his good life, and great know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the intereſts of Princes, in which he hath ſignaliz'd himſelf in two Legations. He is adored, if I may ſay ſo, in the Church of <hi>Jeſi,</hi> where he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, and the Pope, who otherwiſe would have need of men of his parts, does not call him thence, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to deprive that City of ſo worthy a Paſtor. And were it their rule to reward Merit, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo great and good but would fall to his ſhare, but private intereſt denies it him. I ſhould readily give him my vote, were it required, knowing I ſhould therein at the ſame time both ſatisfie my conſcience, and ſerve my Country, which I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand how really he loves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aquaviva,</hi> a <hi>Neapolitan,</hi> was preferred before an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other whom Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> deſired, for ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations repreſented to him by <hi>Donna Olimpia,</hi> who foreſeeing the Pope could not long ſurvive, thought it good policy to ſtrengthen her Family by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of ſuch noble perſons as might protect her on occaſion But ſhe deceived her ſelf, regarding one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the merits of the perſons, and not conſidering whether ſhe ſhould receive all thoſe acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and retributions which men of honor are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd to return at need. He hath, however, a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular applauſe, but I cannot tell whether the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> are ſatisfi'd with him, ſince he did not ſeem to give them any content in the Conclave. But I am very much taken with his expreſſions, which ever tend to the publick good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gondi,</hi> or as he is called at preſent, <hi>de Rets,</hi> hath made the world talk of him, both before and ſince
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135322:40"/> his promotion to be Cardinal: before, becauſe he was as it were the Scourge, that excited troubles in all occurrences, that admitted of the leaſt pretence to thwart the preſent Government: and ſince, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his authority being encreaſed, he preſumed his importunities againſt <hi>Mazarin</hi> and his Partiſans would become more effectual, and that onely for his particular intereſt, and to make himſelf famous in the adminiſtration of affairs. It cannot be denied but <hi>Mazarin</hi> was in a kind of dream when he named him for that Dignity, and committed a very great error therein, not forecaſting the event of it. And indeed, Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> reproached him highly for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing and dealing unhandſomely with one of that Dignity, whom both himſelf and all <hi>France</hi> had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> by their recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations. But this does not make good the too bold pretences of the Eccleſiaſtical power, which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes, it is unlawful for great Princes to reſtrain the exorbitancies of a Cardinal, that endeavours to trouble the peace of the Country. There were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Aſſemblies at <hi>Rome</hi> to conſult a way, whereby, without prejudice to the Cardinal Dignity, they might allay his diſcontent, but it was very difficult, ſince thoſe of <hi>France</hi> required ſecurity that he ſhould breed no diſturbance, and thoſe in <hi>Rome</hi> could not reſolve to do it, becauſe the means propounded was to give away his Church at <hi>Paris</hi> to another, and keep him out of <hi>France,</hi> without leaving him deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of what was neceſſary for his maintenance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles Barberino</hi> is the third Cardinal of that Family, which is rarely ſeen; but that which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves more admiration, is, that this exceſs of favour proceeded from a Pope, who had made it his task to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135322:41"/> eclipſe, not to ſay deſtroy, that Houſe; ſo evident it is, that ſelf-intereſt over-ſways the minds of men, making thoſe that were the moſt inveterate enemies to become the moſt endeared friends. This recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, and the alliance that was made betwixt theſe Families, was the work of <hi>Donna Olimpia,</hi> who prudently conſidered, that if the Pope ſuffer'd this enmity to continue, he would be expoſed thereby to the ſame inconveniencies they had brought upon others. This reflexion pleaſed, and was ſeconded by a moſt advantagious reciprocal union. Nor was there any cauſe of ſcruple that the Pope joyned Purple to Purple in the ſame Family, conſidering the excellent qualities of this young man, who ſhewed an extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary wit and modeſty to all men, and who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying himſelf wholly to the nobleſt ſtudies, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced his birth-right in favour of his younger Brother, to make himſelf a Church-man; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, he is a very good Clergy-man, who never medles with any other kind of buſineſs. He depends abſolutely on the Cardinal <hi>Francis,</hi> and conforms himſelf wholly to his manner of life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pio,</hi> a <hi>Ferrarian,</hi> is of a Family known to your moſt Serene Lordſhips for its Nobility, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of its Branches, which ſhall make me ſay the leſs of him. He does not enjoy his health perfectly though he be but young, and may perhaps leave his Church at <hi>Ferrara,</hi> becauſe the air of <hi>Rome</hi> better agrees with him, where he hath acquir'd a great deal of wealth, and intends to ſettle himſelf altogether. He glories in the natural affection he hath towards your moſt Serene Signiory, as of a thing he much values and moſt highly eſteems.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:135322:41"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Aldobrandin,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> but originary of <hi>Florence,</hi> is the onely remainder of a Papal Family, founded upon ſeven Great-grand-children, Nepvews of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the VIII, who were ſo extreme robuſt, that one would have judged their Line eternal, and yet this Branch is withered. To find a Cardinal of this Family, as the Princeſs <hi>Roſſano</hi> deſired, who is the ſole Hegreſs of all that Eſtate, they were fain to ſeek out this ſmall Courtier, who ſprings from the ſame Stock indeed, but by reaſon of his poverty was neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected even of his own kindred. This example, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with many others, ſhould make the Pope's clearly know, as well as their kindred, that what ever care and pains they take to raiſe their Family, it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſucceeds or continues long, God not being pleaſed to ſuffer thoſe Grandeurs, which are founded on the Church's Patrimony, to ſtand as they would have it. And who ever would be pleaſed to look over the Hiſtory of the Popes, where their Families are regiſtred ſhall find this an infallible Truth: for one ſhall diſcover, that either they were quite extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed, or ſuch as were left remaining became re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to a condition below a mean Fortune: This Cardinal doth acknowledge, that all he hath came from that Princeſs, who was willing to ſhow her ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments to the blood of the <hi>Aldobrandinos,</hi> and now, by ſhowing himſelf worthy, as he hath done, of the honour conferred upon him, and gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a good opinion of every one, upon all occaſions, he patiently expects the time which may prove more favourable to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vidman</hi> ſtaid longer here than he ſaid he would do when he went from <hi>Rome,</hi> where he was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed with the immature death of Count <hi>David</hi> his
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135322:42"/> Brother, for whom the whole Court was very ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful; becauſe thoſe Lords, beſides the good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune they have had to ſee their Family ſo well ſtored with all ſorts of riches, do ſo win the affections of all people by their ſweet converſe, that there is none but are raviſh'd at their proſperity. The Cardinal is alſo an excellent natur'd man, who, to all his other good qualities, adds a moſt tender love towards his Country, which is reciprocally obliged to make their acknowledgments to him upon every occaſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Spada</hi> of <hi>Luca,</hi> is a Prelate who was emploi'd in <hi>Urban</hi>'s time in the affairs of greateſt confidence, and he held the ſame credit in the time of Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> which is an evident teſtimony that he hath excellent qualities. In his Legation to <hi>Ferrara</hi> he did you all the good Offices that you could expect from that good Neighbourhood; and when your Ambaſſadors were received in that City in their paſſage to <hi>Rome,</hi> he out-did all the Miniſters of the Apoſtolique Chair in expreſſions of civility; whence I draw this conſequence, that he very perfectly knows your Lordſhips worths, and the great obligations which are due to you from the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gualtieri D'Orviete</hi> is <hi>Donna Olimpia</hi>'s Creature, who having power to do what ſhe would, brought this man and another that depended wholly upon her, to promotion, by caſting duſt in the Pope's eyes that he might not ſee what ſhe did, not caring whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he were pleaſed or not, after ſhe made him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the fault. This Cardinal was not at <hi>Rome</hi> during my abode, he reſides at his Church at <hi>Fermo,</hi> where he can yet, himſelf, hardly believe he is awake, and really in poſſeſſion of what he holds. There is
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:135322:42"/> little good to be ſaid of him, and that you may judge this a truth, it may ſuffice to tell you, it was a work of the Brain of that Woman.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Odeſcalco de Como</hi> hath the <hi>Lombard</hi> way of acting, which is to ſay, ingenious and franck, and truly he is held to be without malice. He does not profeſs any skill in Politiques, but wants not for judgment, and makes good uſe of it; in time and place convenient. I have nothing to alledge againſt him, ſince the Court finds no fault with him; when this man is mention'd they ſpeak briefly, without making any reflection of his good or bad qualities, which is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing proof that there is more good than hurt in him, becauſe at Court they pardon none they can except againſt. I believe your moſt Serene Signiory may confide in a perſon of his humor, when he makes proteſtation of his affection towards you, as he hath done every time I was with him.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Ottobuono</hi> for his ſweet and charming con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation is beloved of all the Court, nor are there any but do wiſh him a greater dignity than he hath: and truly he hath rendred himſelf worthy of it by his continued labours and vigilancy: and the rather, becauſe by his actions, accompani'd with ſo much civility to all the world; and his judgment in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aging buſineſs of conſequence, he hath made it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent that he deſerves one ſhould confide in him. The City of <hi>Breſcia</hi> is too narrow a limit for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of his Virtues: and the expences he makes would have been better employed in ſome Legation, or ſome conſiderable employment at Court, where, to ſpeak truth, ſuch weak men do reſide, that either for the ſucceſs in an affair, or for want of chooſing
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135322:43"/> the readieſt and ſafeſt ways, they do even diſpleaſe thoſe whom they moſt favour.</p>
            <p>But as for his exile from Court, which we may term honourable, the cauſe thereof can be attributed to nothing elſe, but the knowledge they have of his eminent virtues, as well for that ordinarily Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue is looked upon with an envious eye, as becauſe he did in the Conclave endeavour earneſtly to unite the oppoſite parties, who wavered and obſtructed all other deſigns. All I can ſay to your Excellencies of this Lord, is, that the affection he bears his Native Country is the moſt tender and hearty that can be deſired in any of your moſt Serene Republique's Subjects, and whatever favours you beſtow, you can never place them better than on a man, who, like this ſame now mention'd, is wholly diſpoſed to prefer the publique intereſt in all occaſions before his own.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Maldachino</hi> is very well, the Pope was very careful to make him go and take the aire of the <hi>Campagnia</hi> for a good while, whence he returned at the intreaties of the Cardinals, who took that abſenting for an exile: The <hi>Spaniards</hi> were not much allarm'd at his change, and declaration for <hi>France.</hi> Yet muſt it be ſaid in his praiſe, that he did very wiſely, in ſeeking the ſupport and gaining the favour of a great King. Nay, there is ſome generoſity in it, becauſe there is no appearance he was moved out of intereſt; ſince <hi>Mazarin</hi> is not a perſon likely to beſtow any great reward upon him, whether it be out of his natural inclination to parſimony, or ſome fixed deſign to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate and reduce the vaſt expences of that Nation, drained by ſo long a War, or ſome more hidden and refined politique conſideration, it being certainly a
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:135322:43"/> pure folly to waſte the Exchequer in Penſions for the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi> Beſides, nothing is more apparent than this, that the way to gain thoſe people is to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect them. Intereſt and Fear would ſoon reunite them, and make them look towards <hi>France</hi> for ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, did they fear they were abandon'd to the dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful power of <hi>Spain:</hi> all the humility of ſubmiſſion, and art of compliance would then be put in practiſe to make ſure of, and draw the <hi>French</hi> to their ſide to oppoſe that ambitious Neighbour, who ſurrounding the Pope with <hi>Millan</hi> and <hi>Naples,</hi> may devour him when he hath the mind to it. I have viſited him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome occaſions, but never much regarded his diſcourſe, which ſtill tended to make me believe he is very much a ſervant to your moſt Serene Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Borromeo,</hi> a <hi>Milanois,</hi> a Lord of a conſiderable Birth, hath ever given teſtimony in thoſe employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments he hath had, of a ſtrict ſecreſie, great mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and ſincerity, which are qualities rarely lodged together in a man that is in power or command. He doth at preſent exerciſe the charge of Legat in <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magnia</hi> with much praiſe, not giving any cauſe of complaint under his Government. I cannot but give a fair judgment of his Sentiments for the publique good, on which that of your moſt Serene Republique is neceſſarily depending, which he aſſured me of the laſt time I viſited him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Imperiale,</hi> a <hi>Genoeſe,</hi> is a man fit for Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who quickly apprehends where any evil is, and hath capacity enough to apply the remedy. He hath alſo a free heart, which will not eaſily yield when he finds on which ſide there is more reaſon.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135322:44"/> Yet cannot I tell whether he would ſucceed well if he had the Soveraign command, becauſe he is a <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noeſe,</hi> and prepoſſeſs'd with the Maxims of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, which pretend to attain to that in a ſhort time, to which other Potentates could not arrive but by a ſucceſſion of many ages; and this may perhaps be one of the cauſes will exclude him from any higher advancement. In the mean time, he makes very powerful proteſtations, that he will ever ſide with thoſe who ſtand for the Liberty of <hi>Italy,</hi> which is to ſay in good <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that he will ſide with your moſt Serene Republique.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſtalli,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> hath acted ſeveral parts at the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> in a ſhort time. He was a Prelate of a mean Fortune; ſince that he was made a Cardinal. He was of kindred, and ſupported by Pope <hi>Innocent</hi>'s Niece, who would ſpeak all, and do all, at that time when he was made Cardinal He was in <hi>Pamfilio</hi>'s Family in quality of a Nepvew: a while after he was rejected as unworthy of that Title, exiled from <hi>Rome,</hi> and almoſt caſt into the Precipice: but a little after the death of <hi>Innocent</hi> he ſomewhat recovered himſelf again, yet could not make them reſtore what they had taken. In fine, he found relief in the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Catholique King, who hath beſtowed ſome Largeſs upon him, which hath ſet him in a pretty good poſture. The Hiſtory of the ſtrange turns he hath been ſubject to, would be very curious, but it being too prolix, I ſhall paſs it by; becauſe, likewiſe, ere this Writing appears, no doubt but the Relations of thoſe times will ſet forth the truth of it. There can be nothing more intricate than the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of that Family, which then governed; for on the one ſide, the Pope's Niece and her Confederates
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:135322:44"/> were ever making ſome enterprize, and on the other the Cardinal <hi>Panciroli,</hi> who was then the chief Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of State, countermined them, and either of theſe ſcoffed at that Pope before his face; becauſe, although he had wit enough, yet he had not the judgment or way to make thoſe ſtand in awe of him, who were the moſt obliged to him.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, this Cardinal, after he had un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergone ſo many different Fortunes, attained to his eaſe and quiet, yet without any great repute or eſteem, being more addicted to follow his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, than to ſerve the Publique; and therefore I cannot inform you what his affection is towards this Republique.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Albici,</hi> of <hi>Cenata,</hi> is a man, who finding he can raiſe himſelf no higher by the ways of eminent vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, is reſolved to try what he can do by his extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies; and this it is makes him ſpeak ſo freely againſt the corruptions of the times, which he is not ſatisfi'd in doing in private, but taking delight to ſhew his Eloquence, which is not the higheſt that ever was, he diſcourſes of it in publique Oratories, and ſometimes with biting expreſſions, which ſeems to aim at the Popes creatures, who are in command. This is ill reſented at the Palace, but they let him go on, as if they underſtood him not: and yet not being free from failings himſelf, it is wonder'd he ſhould be ſo apt to cenſure others. He hath rather I know not what kind of commerce with the world, than any conſiderable knowledge; and having been choſen by Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> as a perſon fit for Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, he made him a Cardinal, having more reſpect to his being an enemy to <hi>Maculano,</hi> who was hated by this Family, that ſo he might oppoſe all
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135322:45"/> that favour'd him, than to any merit was found to be in himſelf. He ſpeaks very fine things againſt thoſe that ſhew themſelves ſlow and cold in their preſent aſſiſtance of this Signory; but his importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and tedious diſcourſes are but little regarded, nor indeed eſteemed ſincere, becauſe they are always Satyrical.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Azzolino de la Marca</hi> was brought to be Cardinal by thoſe means that prevail moſt at <hi>Rome,</hi> that is to ſay, by diſcovering the defects of others; I ſhall not ſtand here to repeat the ſtory of <hi>Aſtalli</hi>'s fall, cauſed partly by the reports, true or falſe, of this man. It is certain, there are no eminent virtues in him, and if you except but ſome pretty little flaſhes of the Pen, which he learned in the exerciſe of his Office of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary, I ſee nothing extraordinary in him. He ſpends moſt part of his time in amorous entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, while all he does, brings little benefit to the Publique. I never much eſteemed the great care he takes to expreſs the devotion he hath for your Signio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, becauſe I know any thing pleaſes his mind more than thoughts of buſineſs, thinking all his time too ſhort to recreate himſelf.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal <hi>Lantgrave</hi> of <hi>Heſſe,</hi> who is a Lord of a high birth and a generous ſpirit, might have made better uſe of his Talents, as it is believed, in the profeſſion of a Souldier, than of a Gown-man: not but that he hath given ſome good tokens, by proving himſelf a good Catholique, and a good Diſciple in the Maxims of the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> but when it concerns his taking any advantage, as he pretends much, reflecting on what he is, every one withdraws, even the <hi>Spaniards</hi> themſelves, who other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135322:45"/> being wont to ſhew their largeſs towards thoſe of his quality, are yet ſparing to him, not well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending what ſervice they can expect at <hi>Rome</hi> from a Prince, who hath laid aſide his Armour to take up a Cardinal's little Gown: and that which makes them perhaps more diſtaſted with him, is his leaving the Proteſtant Religion to become a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique without any ſtudy or learning, which are moſt neceſſary Ornaments in a Cardinal; eſpecially a ſtranger, that intends to gain any credit near the Pope. Nevertheleſs he does not diſpair but the time may come, when he may ſettle himſelf at <hi>Rome</hi> in the condition others are in there, without any need of ſeeking abroad for aſſiſtance, as he hath been ſorc'd to do when he ſtaid there after the creation of this Pope, being ſtill put to his ſhifts, by reaſon of the few aſſignations he had, inſomuch that he was ſorc'd to be gone for fear of intangling himſelf. He is a Gentleman of a good judgment, who, following the candour, ſo natural to his Country, either blames or praiſes as he finds people deſerve. He ſpeaks of your Signiory in the ſame terms as a very good <hi>Italian</hi> ſhould do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sforza,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> hath given himſelf to the <hi>Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards,</hi> being eaſily drawn to their party, not ſo much for the rich benefices they beſtowed on him, as out of the hatred he bears againſt <hi>Mazarin,</hi> with whom he could never have agreed, had he remained for the <hi>French.</hi> There accrues no benefit to the <hi>Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard</hi> by the gaining of this Cardinal, but onely the reputation of having a man on their ſide of a great birth, and a bold ſpirit: for he hath otherwiſe no great gifts nor any conſiderable adherents beſides the Great Duke, towards whom he ſhows himſelf very
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135322:46"/> reſerv'd. His genious ever inclined more towards the <hi>French</hi> than the <hi>Spaniſh;</hi> yet hath he moulded his humour to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſervice abſolutely, ſince he found how much more certain the <hi>Spanyards</hi> aſſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are than the <hi>French,</hi> and more beneficial than the others could be. This Family hath ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed to have a great deal of affection for your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity, and many of them have had employments under you, which they have performed with a great deal of applauſe from your moſt Serene Republique. This Cardinal does not forget to profeſs oftentimes, that his affection hath the ſame bias.</p>
            <p>Here ends the old College. It remains now that I ſhould ſpeak ſomewhat of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, of four of which, <hi>viz.</hi> the Cardinals <hi>Chigi, Roſpiglioſi, Pallavicini,</hi> and <hi>Bichi,</hi> having diſcourſed enough in the beginning, I ſhall add what may be ſaid of the other five, whom he hath made Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bagni</hi> is a Cavalier, as noble as he is underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the things of Peace and War. The <hi>Spanyards</hi> were doubtful of the Defunct Cardinal his Brother, nor do I believe they put any great confidence in this, whom they know to be very intimate with <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarin,</hi> which they diſcovered by the reproaches of Pope <hi>Innocent,</hi> who found by <hi>Bagni</hi>'s Letters in read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them, that it was <hi>Mazarin</hi> had dictated them, for which he was very ill treated during his Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciature in <hi>France,</hi> the Aſſignments belonging to that Charge being then taken away from him, as an uſeleſs Miniſter: But the preſent Pope, whileſt he was Secretary to <hi>Innocent,</hi> having more wit than he to judge of the actions of a Miniſter, had ſtill an
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135322:46"/> eſteem for him; and the time being come to diſcover his mind, he declared it more by effects than verbal expreſſions, honouring him with the Cardinal Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and admitting him amongſt his Confidents, and that with reaſon, becauſe his Brother and he have ſerved the Apoſtolique State the ſpace of three-ſcore years. He is antient and unhealthful, This Honour falling to his ſhare in a fit time to attend him to his grave.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paulucci</hi> of <hi>Romagnia</hi> hath attained to a great age, thorow many troubles and fatigues, which have gained him a recompence in a time, wherein he hath little other advantage but his hopes, thoſe advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments onely excepted which his friends have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured him: which hapned very ſeaſonably at this time, he not being fit to perform the Functions of a Cardinal, as being blind. He was never endued with much patience, and much retarded the progreſs of his Fortune by often ſpeaking publickly with too much liberty. Otherwiſe he is a good man, but one that is more knowing in the Canon Law, than prudent in his converſe in the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elci</hi> of <hi>Siena</hi> had nor the Title of Nuncio before he was a Cardinal, but he was highly approved by the Pope, and beſides that, of his kindred. And it was eaſie to diſcover by the tenderneſs of the Pope's expreſſions to him, before he brought him to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, that he was enrolled amongſt thoſe he moſt loved. Your moſt Serene Lordſhips know him far better than I do, having had him there as Nuncio a long while amongſt you, with ſuch ſatisfaction as you may well remember. His qualities makes him worthy of the Purple and the Papal Mitre; and I
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135322:47"/> believe he may come to it in time, unleſs the Court grow weary of the <hi>Sienans,</hi> whereof there being al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready three in the Colledge, it is to be thought the number may yet increaſe, if the Pope live as long as he promiſes to himſelf. The thought this Cardinal hath of your moſt Serene Republique could not be more advantagious than they are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bonviſi</hi> of <hi>Leuca,</hi> hath paſſed through all the Offices at Court, ſhewing ſometimes a conſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of fixing there, and otherwhile an inclination to quit it, as it ſeemed in his long abſence he had intended. In this Pope's time, his hopes renewed afreſh, conſidering he had a reſpect to the merits of deſerving perſons: and truly he called him of his own accord, without being courted to it. He was at firſt Maſter of his Holineſs Chamber, and in that Office he improved the good opinion the Pope had of him, ſo that he was compriſed in the firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion together with five other men, who had all parts neceſſary to attain to the Dignities of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals. He hath none but good qualities, and knows how to gain the love and eſteem of others, as well as to love and eſteem others himſelf, and eſpecially thoſe Princes that deſerve moſt, in which number, to my knowledge, he places your moſt Serene Signory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Farneſe,</hi> a <hi>Roman,,</hi> was under <hi>Innocent</hi> for a time the fifth Evangeliſt. That Pope followed his opinion in all things, and eſteemed and made great choice of them, as proceeding from a man very learned, prudent, and of great integrity: afterwards he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliked him, becauſe he ſpake not according to his fancy, and made no more uſe of him, but ſpake of him even in a kind of a deſpiſing way. The preſent Pope, who judges of the merits of men perfectly
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135322:47"/> well, raiſed him to the Office of Majordom, in which he diſcharged himſelf exceeding well, although he had a thouſand other occupations, there being no Aſſembly held to which he was not called, if they treated of any buſineſs of importance. He helped the Family at preſent in command to the purchaſe of the Lands of <hi>Farneſe,</hi> being his juriſdiction, and ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted the means to exclude the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> who in default of this Branch was to ſucceed therein: in fine, having had the Hat for a reward, they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted the Legation of <hi>Bologna</hi> to him, which he performs to the Pope's great ſatisfaction. He is a great Wit, and perhaps greater than were fitting for the Publique, were he Pope: but ſhould he pretend to it, he would find oppoſition, and the greateſt would be the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> with whom he hath never kept any good correſpondence for the intereſt of his Family; therefore the <hi>Spanyards,</hi> out of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance they have for the Duke, and becauſe they have prejudged he hath ſome inclination towards <hi>France,</hi> will do all they can poſſibly to obſtruct his being made Pope.</p>
            <p>The time of the promotion which is to be made in conſideration of the Princes approaches, and ſince it is already made known who ſhall be promoted, I leave that care to the moſt excellent <hi>Sagredo</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form your moſt Serene Lordſhips of their condition and qualities, and ſhall onely add, that as for him that pertains to your Republique, who is to be made Cardinal, I would not ſay any thing of it to the Pope, knowing this favour lights ſtill on thoſe who are moſt agreeable to his Holineſs; it being ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient that your Signory does herein receive an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour equal to thoſe other Crowns without pointing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:135322:48"/> out the incluſion, or the excluſion of any one in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, provided you have no diffidence of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they ſhall promote.</p>
            <p>I could here ſhut up the Liſt of thoſe that make up the grandeur of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſince the Queen of <hi>Sweden</hi> hath made choice of it for her or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary reſidence, and that I hapned to communicate ſometimes with her Majeſty, I ſhall add ſome ſmall matter which I have to ſay concerning this Princeſs.</p>
            <p>At her firſt coming to <hi>Rome</hi> ſhe had ſo little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the grandeur of your State, that ſhe thought it ſtrange your Miniſters ſhould be treated equally with thoſe of the greateſt Kings in Chriſtendom: and therefore when it was told her, that my Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor intended to give her a viſit, ſhe ſeemed in the beginning unwilling to allow him the ſame Honour ſhe granted to the Miniſters of other Princes; but being informed that ſhe miſtook, ſhe condeſcended to do it in the ſame manner as was uſual at Court. She was afterwards fully acquainted with the great ſervice this Republique did to all Chriſtendom, in oppoſing ſingly the dreadful Forces of the common Enemy. And this made her ſhew more complaiſance in often converſing with me; and to have the better occaſions, not regarding her little power ſo much as following the ſentiments of her generoſity, ſhe proffer'd to find out the means to raiſe a Regiment of Infantry for the ſervice of this State, and gave the charge hereof to <hi>Sentinelli</hi> her favourite. But afterwards the difficulty of getting her mony out of <hi>Sweden</hi> being encreaſed, the firſt great heat of her good-will grew cool, ſo that after the order ſhe had given for the receipt of a thouſand Doublons, ſhe made no other aſſignment; all the reſt vaniſhing in ſmoak; as well through the death of <hi>Sentinelli,</hi> who
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:135322:48"/> was uſually there to pay the Soldiers, as the diſgrace of another who till then was thought to be in favour with her Majeſty. However, I omitted not to pay her my reſpects from time to time, in token of my acknowledgment, to which ſhe ever correſponded by actions of great civility. But to ſay truth, that Princeſs is poſſeſſed onely with vain ſpeculations, which are the foundation of thoſe great undertakings ſhe deſignes. And being unwilling to venture the hazard of misfortune, hoping for all ſhe deſires, ſo ſhe thinks every thing that comes in her fancy is very eaſily brought to paſs. And if the news of the King of <hi>Sweden</hi>'s death, which I heard of in my journey homewards, proves true, her want of mony will yet be greater. Indeed, Pope <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> voluntarily engaged himſelf in thoſe great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences were made for her reception at <hi>Rome,</hi> but no man doubts but he repented him of it ſince, when he perceived there was not that ſolidity of judgment in her as had been reported; for ſhe hath made it appear, ſhe is a Woman like others, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as ſubject to defects as any other of that Sex. She hath at preſent begun a courſe of life ſomewhat more moderate, and therefore more durable; and if ſhe would have really perſwaded the world, that it was a knowledge of the true Religion which obliged her to quit her Crown and Kingdom, and paſs into the boſome of another Church and Country, ſhe could not have taken a wiſer reſolution, than to have made her retreat into ſome Monaſtery where ſhe might have been at eaſe, and lead a quiet life free from trouble, and ſuitable to her condition, not as to the greatneſs, but the conveniency of it, and with a liberty to have come out again when ſhe pleaſed. She did not much praiſe the Pope, but ſaid, ſhe was
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135322:49"/> promiſed by him, that he would put her in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to live handſomly; whereas on the contrary ſhe perceived, that his Holineſs kindred had not that eſteem for her they ought to have. She added many other things, which ſhews her to be of a querulous humour, that is, juſt like a Woman that cannot tell what ſhe would have. When I took leave of her, I found her penſive enough at the news of the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condition of the King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> which makes me believe what I heard ſince his death, that ſhe hath left <hi>Rome</hi> and is gone into her Country, the better to ſecure the payments they were engag'd to make her. When ſhe hath done that, if ſhe return to make her abode in <hi>Rome,</hi> many people will be glad of it, but, very few will have any cauſe to be jealous.</p>
            <p>And now, having made known the internal and external qualities of the Pope, and his Kindred, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with thoſe that ſerve him, for aid and counſel in his Government both Politique and Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtique, it is time to examine the internal Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his Holineſs towards Chriſtian Princes, and ſo to conclude by examining what his thoughts are concerning the good and advantage of your moſt Serene Republique, upon which, having made a moſt ſerious reflection, I dare believe that I ſhall be but very little or not at all miſtaken.</p>
            <p>ANd to begin with him, who holds the firſt and higheſt rank, and hath moſt authority amongſt Secular Princes, <hi>viz.</hi> the Emperour, we cannot ſay but the Pope holds very good intelligence or corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with him, ſince at the Election of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:135322:49"/> to the Imperial Crown, he did all he was able to overcome thoſe difficulties the Electors made, who would hardly comply, unleſs ſome ſatisfaction were allowed them which they pretended were due to them: and his Holineſs had much adoe to gain the favour as well of the Eccleſiaſtique as the Secular Electors, not to name the Proteſtants, who being on the one hand perſwaded by the Sollicitations of the <hi>French,</hi> and on the other with-held by the certain knowledge, it was then the onely time to make their conditions better than they had been; for it was much impaired thorow the long continuance of that great Dignity in the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Family: and therefore the Pope ſpeaks very loud of the high ſervices he therein did to his Imperial Majeſty, having juſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to expect he ſhould in retribution do any thing for him again that lies in his power: To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it is evident indeed, that they take all the care imaginable to pleaſe him. Thus at the beginning of this Pope's Government, it was chiefly upon his ſollicitation that the Emperour attaqued the King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> by the invaſion he made upon <hi>Pomerania,</hi> notwithſtanding the many difficulties might have hapned, by reaſon of the danger of breeding new troubles in <hi>Germany</hi> upon pretence of a breach of the Peace at <hi>Munſter,</hi> which the Friends and Allies of the <hi>Swede</hi> might allege: and which, is moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, this was undertaken in a time when the Court was empty of mony, which is a thing that ought ſtill to be had in readineſs upon any ſudden commotion. Nevertheleſs the Pope's perſwaſions prevailed upon the promiſe he made, that if any urgent occaſion required, and they called upon him, he would remit them a good ſum from <hi>Rome;</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135322:50"/> they did much want it, and craved it with much earneſtneſs, they were put off with many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes to evade the promiſe, as it is the cuſtome of that Court to diſingage themſelves, and leave thoſe others engaged who confide too much in them. And though this were huſh'd up by the Imperialiſts, yet it hath made them ſomewhat forgetful of the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Pope pretended from this Court, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially conſidering beſides this, that the Pope's en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour for the election of <hi>Leopoldus,</hi> was not ſo much to hinder the choice of any other, as out of this reſpect the Pope had, that if the Imperial Dignity ſhould fall on any other Prince, it were not certain whether the Authority of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> would be ſtill continued over the <hi>German</hi> Catholiques, or whether the Pope's Conſtitutions would be obſerv'd with the great reverence as now they are, under the Government of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which hath been ever very obſervant in the Cuſtoms and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of that Court. I therefore hold it for true and certain, that the Pope and Emperor will at preſent keep a fair agreement, and the more, becauſe in the Treaty of Peace between the two Crowns of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> their intereſts were little conſidered, ſince amongſt all thoſe that were mentioned and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed, theſe were placed laſt of all, at which they were both diſpleaſed and murmured to themſelves; yet both diſſembled this diſcontent, which did in ſome manner help to tie them the more ſtrictly to their former confidence, and made the Emperour give ear more readily to the Counſels of the Pope, When the troubles in the North increaſed. The Pope knows, that in the Emperor's Court perhaps he hath more credit than in any other in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:135322:50"/> which will make him put thoſe deſigns in execution, he hath told me of more than once, which is, to put the Emperour upon a War that will prove advantagious to Chriſtendome by an eaſie way, but wholly reſerv'd to himſelf. Perhaps the preſent juncture of affairs may render the thing more feaſible than at another ſeaſon; yet when his Holineſs told me his deſign, whatſoever reflexion I made, yet could I not apprehend either how or when it might be brought to paſs. Nor do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he would find much repugnance on the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror's part, having a lively ſpirit, and great diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to engage upon any good counſel: but if there ſhould be much mony required to carry it on, it would be eſteemed a Chymera, becauſe the Princes of this age have an averſion to all propoſitions of rupture that are made, and the Emperour more than any, eſpecially now his Coffers are drained, and part of thoſe under his power obey not their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour very willingly, whilſt others would be glad to ſee him fall, and every one is unwilling to disburſe. The Emperour hath no other Miniſter at <hi>Rome</hi> but the Cardinal <hi>Colonne,</hi> who bearing ever a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Pope for the Intereſt of his Family, cannot do his Imperial Majeſty any great ſervice in his Negotiations, but all paſſes thorow the hands of the Lord <hi>Caraffe,</hi> Nuncio in the Imperial Court, who exerciſes that Office with as great ſatisfaction to either ſide, as he did with profit, when he reſided near your moſt Serene Lordſhips.</p>
            <p>The <hi>French</hi> Nation does, perhaps, beſt of any apprehend the Genious of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and knows the readieſt ways to withdraw themſelves
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135322:51"/> out of ſuch inconveniencies wherein other Princes do inſenſibly engage themſelves. They eſteem and revere the Apoſtolique Chair in a Souvereign de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, and tender all the reſpect that can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired from a Prince truly Catholique and pious; but for all this they are very clear-ſighted and wary to maintain their Prerogatives, and prevent the Eccleſiaſtiques, who at preſent endeavour to extend their power over all, from bringing any prejudice upon them. No ſooner is any decree made in the Sanctury of <hi>Rome</hi> which reliſhes of ambition, but it is carefully examined by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, who oftentimes, without any qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, gives judgment againſt ſuch decrees, and after lets the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> cry out againſt them as they pleaſe. Many times alſo upon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſion and negative of what it contains they tell the Popes their Leſſon, when they go beyond their bounds in ſeeking to diminiſh the Royal Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſo that they are moſt commonly conſtrained to bow, and give ſatisfaction. Which happens ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rarely, when the Popes have to do with any other Princes, how great ſoever they be, for out of divers reſpects they dare not uſe that liberty of ſpeech which is natural to the <hi>French;</hi> which makes the Popes leſs haſty to innovate the Prerogatives of that Kingdome, knowing that by bringing in ſome Novelty they do not advance their buſineſs, but rather wrong themſelves, at leaſt in their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation if no other way, they being ſtill obliged either to relax, or not to ſee that put in execution which they had reſolved upon.</p>
            <p>I could not find that the Pope had any averſion for that Nation, as ſome have believed, I onely
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:135322:51"/> perceived that he condemned their new form of Government, becauſe he thought it was invented by <hi>Mazarin,</hi> the onely object of all the injuries I ever heard from his Holineſs mouth. But at the ſame time he complained of <hi>Mazarine,</hi> he ever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termixed ſome praiſes of the King and Queen, and ſomewhat in commendations of the flouriſhing ſtate of that Kingdom, to whom that unhappineſs was befallen, as he ſaid, to be governed by one ſingle Man, who, without any regard to the publick good, ſought onely his own private intereſt; but when the firſt news of the Peace was ſpread abroad, he was a long time very penſive, and of opinion, that it was fit to take good conſideration of what paſſed; ſtill doubting that <hi>Mazarin,</hi> by this pleaſing and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come news, had a deſign to lull other Princes aſleep, according to his uſual policy, and after ſome parade of his good intents, to avoid the world's blame, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin again a War with more fury than ever. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, finding there was really a Treaty, and being confirmed in it by his own Miniſters, he could do no leſs than expreſs ſome ſigns of content, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that having never asked any thing of God with more affection and deſire than the making of this Peace, it was indifferent to him whether it was brought about by his or any other means, he having this comfort at leaſt, that the Articles could not differ very much from thoſe, which he a long time before by his many conſultations and cares had framed to the ſame end. But, for all this, the Pope was ſomewhat netled, though he would not ſhew it, that it ſhould be ſaid, The Peace was now brought about by that ſame perſon, he had in all companies accuſed as the onely diſſenter and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135322:52"/> of what he undertook to make them agree upon: and that the <hi>Spanyards</hi> ſhould now come to acknowledge him the Author of the peace and quiet of their State, that had ever been their Anta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goniſt, and oppreſſed them, to the great prejudice of the Catholique Religion: And although the Pope made a large diſcourſe in praiſe of <hi>Mazarin,</hi> to the Gentleman that came to <hi>Rome</hi> about the Diſpenſation for the Marriage, briefly running over all the particulars therein, and making it paſs for one of the greateſt and happieſt actions that ever was effected by any of his Predeceſſors, or Miniſters; yet upon ſome occaſions hapning ſince, it was eaſie to take notice, that his Holineſs ſtill retains part of his old jealouſie; and were there no other proof, that which paſſed concerning the Arch-biſhop of <hi>Ambrun,</hi> Ambaſſador from the King of <hi>France</hi> to your moſt Serene Lordſhips, were a ſufficient one, which hath occaſion'd the great diſcontent that hath laſted ſo long time, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not yet be compoſed. For the Pope ſtill pleads this, that although there were many other men in <hi>France</hi> of greater probity, and fitter for that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment than he, yet <hi>Mazarin</hi> would put it upon an Eccleſiaſtique, that ſo becauſe of the integrity required therein, and the inconveniencies which would follow, he might be ſure to find out ſome oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of diſcontent when he pleaſed. Your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips cannot believe how much heat the Pope ſhewed in maintaining this opinion, for although the difference were a trifle, the action not being in it ſelf ſo conſiderable as the Church-men would have it to be, yet I have been more puzzled about it than in matters of the higheſt importance, having
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:135322:52"/> had much ado to perſwade the Pope, not to believe your moſt Serene Lordſhips took part rather with the <hi>French</hi> than him; who by your refuſing to receive his Nuncio in a habit different from the ordinary garb, you ſhewed how little you cared the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Chair ſhould maintain its Prerogatives, and that Authority that God alone can limit. I omitted not to ſhew his Holineſs, moſt ſincerely, that the end and onely aim of your Lordſhips was to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent greater diſcontents that might have followed, and to abſtain from thoſe kind of Novelties which in time might have been made cuſtomary. I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated ſome of the moſt confiding and judicious Cardinals, to mediate about it, that ſo ſmall a matter might not make diſſention, but that your Lordſhips ſincerity might be looked on with a pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent eye. But the Pope would not be ſatisfi'd with reaſon, who continuing his firſt complaints, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>That it was a premeditated buſineſs of</hi> Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin<hi>'s, who had not been content to trouble the whole world by blowing the coals of diſſention and war, but would now, if he could, make them find bitterneſs, too, in the very beginning of a Peace.</hi> He waſted a great part of the Audience before his anger could be abated, in theſe and the like kind of diſcourſes. And I doubt whether things can ſtand long as they are, unleſs the <hi>French</hi> reſolve to recall their Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador from hence, as I think all the world is bound to do what they can, to maintain the Peace by ſuch common ſatisfactions, hoping that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after things of ſo ſmall importance ſhall not inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt our greater joy and quiet. However, I think, notwithſtanding this I have related, I may truly tell your moſt Serene Lordſhips, it is moſt likely, that
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135322:53"/> although the Pope and the King of <hi>France</hi> are not always abſolutely ſatisfi'd with each other, yet they would ſcarce be brought to ſuch terms as ſhould cauſe a rupture: they being likely to keep and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their amity, not onely during the life of this Pope and King, but of their Succeſſors. And there are two reaſons that oblige me to believe ſo; the firſt is, that the Popes finding they cannot intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce their Innovations according to their own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, by force and rigour, into that Kingdom, to the prejudice of the privileges of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church, and the notable diminution of their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Juriſdiction, will forbear it, that they may not undergo the contempt of ſeeing their Decrees re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, and their Authority deſpiſed. Whence it will follow, that the Cauſe ceaſing, thoſe Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which are the Effects, will ceaſe likewiſe. The ſecond, which is purely Politique, may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to this, That although the Popes have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired great power over the <hi>Spanyard,</hi> by their having ſeveral times extremely obliged them, and do in their Country exerciſe an Authority not at all diſputed, nevertheleſs they cannot but have ſome jealouſie and fear, leſt that Monarchy ſhould one day open its eyes, and endeavour to eaſe themſelves of thoſe great burthens the Clergy have inſenſibly laid on their backs; and becauſe if that ſhould happen, it may be the thunder of the Cenſures, and Temporal power of the Church, would prove inſufficient to oppoſe that danger. The Pope's have therefore made it their Maxim to keep the Amity of the <hi>French,</hi> as a means thereby to help themſelves in caſe there ſhould any change or ſtirs happen on the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> Some Cardinals have at
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:135322:53"/> times entertained me with diſcourſe on this ſubject, not in ſuch plain terms, but however in ſuch a way, that I could eaſily perceive that they ſee clearer and farther then ſome Princes imagine they do. When ever the <hi>French,</hi> laying aſide their ſuſpition of the Clergies covetouſneſs, ſhall endeavour or deſire to be at greater amity with the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> there is no cauſe to fear but it would ſucceed, becauſe of their conformity in Religion, and becauſe of their own intereſt: who, if they ſhould trouble the peace of <hi>Rome,</hi> would compel them to unite themſelves more firmly with the <hi>Spanyard,</hi> a thing the <hi>French</hi> will endeavour to obſtruct as much as poſſibly they can.</p>
            <p>If we ſhould judge of things according to the intereſt of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Pope <hi>Alexander</hi>'s inclination, we need not doubt but the <hi>Spanyards</hi> poſſeſs the affection of his Holineſs more than any other. The intereſt of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> conſiſts in this, that for the moſt part, the mony wherewith it is glutted above all the other Cities in <hi>Italy,</hi> comes in greateſt abundance from the States of the Catholique King, where the Eccleſiaſtical Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal is held in Sovereign veneration, all the States of that Monarchy having their recourſe thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to the great profit of the Officers, who have a ſhare in the Firſt-fruits and many other things, according to their Quality, and their Offices. And as for the Pope's inclination, provided he otherwiſe have a general zeal for the good of Chriſtendom, and the propagation of the Faith, and that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main ſtedfaſt in theſe two things, as I believe he doth, I think he may and ought to have a more
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:135322:54"/> particular affection for that Nation, whoſe Maxim it is, Not to admit of any other Religion in their Dominions but the <hi>Roman Catholique,</hi> and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the power they have to advance it: But in truth, things are not carri'd thus, for whether the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> believes that all the <hi>Spanyards</hi> do in pretence of Religion is rather out of ſelf-intereſt, or whether this Court is perſwaded they ought ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely to rule over thoſe that will never fall foul on her, how great ſoever the inconveniencies are they lie under, it is ever obſerv'd in all the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences ariſing betwixt <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> that after a great and long conteſt, the Agreement is moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly made to the Popes content, and the diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſomewhat of the Catholique King's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences; and when buſineſſes have thus hapned to the diſadvantage of that Monarchy, other Princes have alſo received a notable prejudice thereby: for when the Pope or his Miniſters have once car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri'd ſo high a hand over the <hi>Spanyard</hi> as to make him yield, they preſently make uſe of the opportunity to quell or confound thoſe that would do otherwiſe, or at leaſt to induce them not to refuſe that, to which ſo great a Monarchy as <hi>Spain</hi> hath acquieſc'd. This ſtratagem may be effectual when they treat with inferior Princes, who are not able upon every conteſt they have with <hi>Rome</hi> to take Arms: but both the Pope and his Miniſters decline all theſe ways, when they have to deal with the <hi>French,</hi> who, when the Clergy preſs'd them, by this example of the <hi>Spanyards,</hi> to condeſcend to things which were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to them, ſoon gave them an anſwer which ſtopped their mouthes: Nay my ſelf being once earneſtly ſollicited to preſs your Lordſhips for a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135322:54"/> revocation of the Ordinance, which prohibits the Clergy from purchaſing any immovables, upon an example alleaged of the practiſe of <hi>Spain,</hi> and the other Territories of his Catholique Majeſty, did give for anſwer, That the reaſons which oblig'd that great and vaſt Monarchy to ſuffer it, were not current here, becauſe this Republique being but a petty or little State, and the Clergy extraordinarily encreaſed in wealth, if they were ſuffered ſtill to purchaſe and never to alienate, our poſterity could expect no other than to be one day driven out of this<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Venice</hi> is built on a Marſh.</note> Marſh, and and perhaps out of all her Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories on the firm Land. And to this are all thoſe Principalities reduc'd, who, not content with that ſubjection they owe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as the Univerſal Mother of Chriſtians, have ſubmitted to, and followed the Pope's deſires in things indifferent: not that they do at once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ſeveral things of difficulty, but ſometimes one thing and then another, and thus by little and little they gain ſo much as doth both diminiſh and limit the Temporal Power: and ſo when Princes ſhall think themſelves Maſters, they will find their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſo eclips'd and manacl'd, that they will be aſtoniſh'd to ſee another maſter them at their own homes. Thoſe who are acquainted with their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortions at <hi>Naples,</hi> and perhaps in all the other Dominions of <hi>Spain,</hi> of the Officers of the <hi>Roman</hi> Treaſury, as well in matters of<note n="*" place="bottom">A certain Fee levi'd by the Eccleſiaſtical Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber at the death of a Clergy-man that hath no power to make a Will.</note> Deſpoiling, as in
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:135322:55"/> the gathering up of what is raiſed for the Fabrick of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> which they alſo impoſe on meer Laicks, cannot but admire, that the Miniſters of <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould be ſo drouſie, as not to obſerve with what Empire void of all diſcretion, and with what inſolency they treat the Perſons and Goods of their Subjects. Let your moſt Serene Signory, therefore, give thanks to the Divine Bounty, that hath preſerved her from theſe confuſions, and given her the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and courage to defend both her ſelf and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects from the violence of ſuch Strangers, confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ever in the antient and true Faith; but alſo giving her at the ſame time the judgment to diſcern what is due to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and what to God. It is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that if the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſtill keep their eyes as cloſe ſhut as they have hitherto done, they cannot expect ſo great a Tempeſt from any other part as from the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> when upon any acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent there ſhall ariſe diſſention amongſt them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe people that are Subjects to the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Family being hugely poſſeſſed with Religion, and fully perſwaded, that the Sanctuary of <hi>Rome</hi> is that alone which can either beſtow or deprive them of Eternal Salvation, if in the commencement of a rupture the Popes ſhould proceed to Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or a Revocation of Indulgences which they have liberally allowed the Catholique Kings, it is beyond all doubt that a general combuſtion would follow thereupon, which might occaſion the revolt of all the Subjects of that great Empire, and ſo the forfeit of the peace and ſecurity of the <hi>Spanyards</hi> would flow from his too great obedience, wherein they imagine their chief ſtrength and power does conſiſt. But perhaps likewiſe the good
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135322:55"/> Genious of thoſe Kingdomes will ſuggeſt ſuch means as may prevent theſe inconveniencies, and (the preſent Age not having been happy in that Monarchy, by reaſon of the few virtuous Men that have been her late Souvereigns) fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Ages may produce more excellent ones, and compenſe her paſt diſorders, by preventing thoſe which might happen probably to her hereafter. In effect, if with attention we conſider the preſent poſture of things in the world, it greatly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns Chriſtendome to have a Potent Prince, who in ſuch dangers, whereinto the power of the <hi>Turks</hi> may in an inſtant and unprovided caſt her, might ſuddenly make head againſt them without making of Leagues and expecting Foreign aid, which cannot be compaſſed but by length of time, and is a great retardment. And if Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome had had in this preſent juncture of things a powerful Prince to have thus ſuccour'd her, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps your moſt Serene Signory had not been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to the condition ſhe is now in: And, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, on her ſecurity depends all what the Monarchy of <hi>Spain</hi> poſſeſſes in <hi>Italy.</hi> But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to what I ſaid, Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of all thoſe reaſons he hath to make him love <hi>Spain</hi> and her King; and does often tell this to the Miniſters of other Princes; but in ſuch a manner however, as if it ſeemed that the benefits which the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> receiveth from the <hi>Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards</hi> were not ſo conſiderable, as to hinder the Pope from denying them from time to time thoſe favours which they crave of him, as having au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority not to grant all to thoſe Children he moſt tenders what they ſhall deſire, but onely that
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:135322:56"/> which will be for their greateſt good, and higheſt, ſpiritual, advantage. His Holineſs hath made complaint, for that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Miniſters have been too reſerved and ſecret towards him, in not communicating to him the Treaty of Peace, pretending that having ever believed the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions on their part were more plauſible than thoſe which were ſhaped in <hi>Mazarin</hi>'s Cloſet, they did him wrong in obſerving ſo rigorouſly that Seal of Secreſie which <hi>Mazarin</hi> had im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed on them: And although they endeavour all they can to calm his diſcontented thoughts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, urging that it was conceal'd in the ſame manner from the Emperour, and even from the Republique, which had been ſo long time employ'd about the Treaty. He is not, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, ſatisfi'd with this excuſe, but replies, <hi>That they ought to make a difference between Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Princes and a Pope, who aimed at no other thing but to find out the means to give that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to all Chriſtendom, and not have left that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to a man who had ſtudi'd all the devices ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable to obſtruct ſo great a happineſs.</hi> After all this, I conclude, that the Pope hath juſt reaſon to love the <hi>Spanyards,</hi> not ſo much becauſe they contributed to his Exaltation, as becauſe their Arms have put a ſtop to the fury of Heretiques, and their Country brings in the Riches and opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency to the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> and I believe he doth truly love them, but having found that his Predeceſſors had taken the way to have moſt commonly ſome conteſts with the Catholique Court, he will not ſwerve from it, eſteeming theſe diſputes do in ſome reſpects encreaſe the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:135322:56"/> reputation of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and from thence hath a fair opportunity to gain an eſteem of other Princes; not declining my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Propoſition, That the more the <hi>Spanyards</hi> condeſcend to the Pope's will, the more will they prejudice themſelves, and the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they do acknowledge to be due from them to the Apoſtolique Seat, may one day produce moſt dangerous effects, unleſs they fore-arm themſelves by ſuch precautious means, as they ſhall judge moſt proper againſt the pretenſions of the Eccleſiaſtiques, thereby to put their Monarchy in a better poſture of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Poland</hi> ſubſiſts becauſe God hath affiſted him: For otherwiſe, had he reli'd on thoſe hopes the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> had given him to ſupply him with Money, his enemies had triumph'd over him, and the total loſs of that Kingdom would have been ſuch a leading to other Provinces, as might have wrought the manifeſt danger of eſtabliſhing a Power in thoſe parts which would have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come formidable to all <hi>Europe.</hi> God be praiſed that we are ſo happy as to ſee every one return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his own home again, his neighbouring Princes beginning to ſtickle in that War, as they ought to do; whereas nothing to purpoſe could have been expected from them, had the preſſing affairs of Chriſtendom ſummoned them to the defence of their own States. The Pope talks loudly of the good Offices he did for the Religion and Countries of the Catholique
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135322:57"/> Princes at that juncture. But the <hi>Polonians</hi> and <hi>Imperialiſts</hi> ſpeak otherwiſe; they profeſs, that at the heighth of all the War they found no great benefit in the exhortations of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, which ſerved for nothing elſe but onely to perſwade their Enemies they had not ſo little amity for them, but that they would ſend them ſuccour from <hi>Rome.</hi> And it was this noiſe and nothing elſe that made it believed, the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Forces were ſo much greater than indeed they were. In the mean time, King <hi>Caſimir,</hi> a good Souldier and good Catholique, finding at preſent his loſſes are nothing ſo great, as he had cauſe to fear they would prove, gives the Pope thanks for what he hath done, and to pleaſe him the more tells him, <hi>That the very words of his Holineſs were not ineffectual for his aſſiſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Savoy</hi> hath had no Miniſter at <hi>Rome</hi> ſince ſome diſcontent given him in Pope <hi>Innocent</hi>'s time: and, indeed, conſidering the little buſineſs he hath there, he needs not entertain any. The preſent Pope, who ſeeks by all means and ways to add luſtre and glory to that Court, which he thinks does conſiſt much in the number of ſuch Miniſters as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide there on the behalf of other Princes, hath declared, that he ſhould be much pleaſed to have an Ambaſſadour from that Duke, as from a Prince to whom the Church is much ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd: This he made known obliquely to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> and the <hi>Duke</hi> her Son, who found it fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to content his Holineſs herein, who would
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:135322:57"/> be willing likewiſe to add luſtre to that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, were there any of them at preſent wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the Purple, to lay the ſurer foundation for the poſterity of the <hi>Chigi,</hi> upon which a certain Marquis, <hi>de la Mojette,</hi> a very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plete Cavalier, preſenting himſelf at <hi>Rome</hi> in quality of Ambaſſador, the Pope expreſs'd a great deal of ſatisfaction thereupon.</p>
            <p>The name of the Grand Duke of <hi>Toſcany</hi> is agreeable to the whole Court, the Pope eſteems him, and in the Conſiſtory hath more than once ſpoken of his Highneſs with a great deal of honour, perhaps becauſe being born his Subject, and the moſt part of his kindred being within his juriſdiction, he believes, that as well out of the reſpect to his birth, as from the conſideration of what may happen, he ought to have all that eſteem for him which he is worthy of. In which this Pope is more praiſe-worthy than the three Popes his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, which were <hi>Clement</hi> VIII, <hi>Paul</hi> V, and <hi>Urban</hi> the VIII, who although they were born in <hi>Toſcany,</hi> did ſo utterly forget what they owed to their Country, and thoſe who were the Princes of it, that they could not be excuſed of ingratitude; but becauſe it is the natural vice of Prieſts, few men reflect upon it; and nevertheleſs this is the cauſe that Princes themſelves do not know whether they ought to be glad that one of their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects is advanced to the Sovereign Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Dignity.</p>
            <pb n="98" facs="tcp:135322:58"/>
            <p>Theſe two Princes for ſome other kind of intereſts receive not that ſatisfaction which they ought to have, he that commands at <hi>Rome</hi> never failing to claſh ſometimes with one of them, and ſometimes the other Prince, and that perhaps to ſhew they are treated alike, and ſo the one hath no more cauſe to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaud the Government than the other. But for all this they negotiate confidently, and as both have the repute of being prudent, they communicate and conſult together when thoſe two Courts have any thing of difference, which doth not a little ſerve to preſerve and maintain their amity.</p>
            <p>Although the <hi>Genoeſe,</hi> after they had been ſome time without a Miniſter at <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe in this Pope's time they had been, as it were, excluded from their pretences, have of late ſent one thither with ſome hopes of being bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heard for the future: yet I can hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Pope will inovate any thing in their favour, for fear of cauſing ſome diſturbance amongſt the other Princes, who not thinking themſelves inferiour, would not ſuffer them to enjoy greater Prerogatives than themſelves. Every one ſaid at <hi>Rome,</hi> that this Republique deſiring more grandeur than ſhe already hath, would ſuddenly disburſe ſome great ſum to obtain it, which might thereupon be granted, by covering the Contract they might make by ſome ſpecious pretence. All this may be; but the faireſt and the honeſteſt way, in my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:135322:58"/> would be to engage them to ſuccour this Republique with their Squadrons, provided they did not require a greater acknowledgment for this than were due.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> after the fair words they have given him, finds they do in effect deny the ſatisfaction due to his juſt deſires, which tend to furniſh him wherewith to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem his Eſtate of <hi>Caſtro</hi> again. I did not omit, having your Lordſhips Orders, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quit my ſelf of thoſe devoirs to which I was oblig'd, both by the juſtice of his cauſe, and your commands. But after they had turned me every way with ambiguous words, I found that ſomewhat more effectual was required to bring it to paſs. It cannot be deni'd in truth, but they do very much wrong this Duke, for though in the Apoſtolique Chamber they have made an Act which adjudges this Eſtate forfeit, if he redeem it not within a certain prefixed time, yet this Pope, of a milder and more temperate humour than <hi>Innocent</hi> was, ought rather to follow the rules of Equity than the rigour of the Law, by conſidering, that this Eſtate is worth two thirds more than what it is engaged for, and that it could not happen in a worſer time for him to do it, than ſince the Contract was made, all <hi>Lombardy</hi> having been in Arms, and he moreover neceſſitated to ſecure that Eſtate at his own charges, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it were a Feof belonging to the Church, which hath been a very great expence to him.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:135322:59"/> But when one treats with thoſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique Chamber of any thing that concerns their intereſt, one can neither be heard, nor ever get any thing from them upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of reaſon. It is is therefore the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of all Crowns, having conſider'd the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the clauſes of this Contract, to find out ſome way to relieve the Duke of this enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous grievance; and this would be beſt done by the <hi>Spanyards,</hi> to take away all thoſe ſeeds of diſcord from <hi>Italy,</hi> which might ariſe from the like diſcontents: which ſhould it happen, the <hi>Spanyards</hi> would receive the greateſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice thereby, as having moſt to looſe. But one good word from the Pope makes them paſs by any thing, and keeps them from doing or ſaying ought that may diſpleaſe him in the leaſt: and I perceive already, that the new Ambaſſadour from <hi>Spain, D. Lewis Ponze de Leon,</hi> is come with a deſign not to negotiate any thing but what ſhall pleaſe the Pope; and for this reaſon will permit the Duke to owe the whole obligation of this buſineſs to Strangers, who afterwards, and that with reaſon, ſhall be recompenſed for it upon oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
            <p>This which I have ſaid of the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> may be appli'd likewiſe to the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> who alleges the greateſt reaſons in the world upon the Subject of <hi>Comacchio,</hi> and what is annexed to it. This proceſs hath been depending before the Court Tribunals
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:135322:59"/> above ſixty years, and yet they cannot obtain a Sentence that the demands of the Houſe of <hi>Eſte</hi> are unjuſt, although the greateſt Lawyers of our times have uſed all their Art to find out ſome plea that might make them let fall their pretences, or at leaſt weaken and invalidate them, and ſupport the Chamber's claim. All that the Counſellors could do, who never want evaſions to ſpin out a buſineſs, hath been to prolong this ſame. And it hath hapned ſeveral times, when they were brought to terms of concluding it by ſome fair compoſition, at the very nick of time when they were juſt ending, they have ſtarted ſome new exceptions to unravel it again, inſomuch that this Suit hath laſted al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, as I ſaid, above threeſcore years. But it were convenient, that at this time when the flames of an univerſal War are extinguiſhed, theſe ſparks, which might perhaps bring all into a combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion again, ſhould be put out likewiſe: and it were reaſonable too, thoſe Crowns ſhould em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy their authority and power to make them leave of that baſe and vile avarice which is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to the whole world. But unleſs they go about it roundly, and ſpeak to the purpoſe in expreſs terms, laying aſide all civility, it will be difficult to bring this about, the affairs of the Chamber of <hi>Rome</hi> being a Gulf that ſwallows all one hath, and whence nothing can be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed no more than from Hell.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Mantoua</hi> is held in ſome conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration at <hi>Romé</hi> by reaſon of the Eſtate he
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:135322:60"/> poſſeſſes, which ſhould oblige all <hi>Italians</hi> to wiſh him proſperity, as the Pope doth, who does herein agree with the other Princes of <hi>Italy.</hi> But otherwiſe he cares little for this Court, by reaſon of the little buſineſſes he hath there. Nor does the Court on their ſide make any great reflexion on his perſon. They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider or look upon him as a Prince, who cannot do better than to follow the ſtream with others, that is to ſay, accommodate himſelf to the Guſto of thoſe who are moſt puiſſant in <hi>Italy,</hi> and particularly your Signory: for in keeping cloſe and well to her, he does at the ſame time do well both for himſelf and the general good.</p>
            <p>We are now come to the laſt, but moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Chapter of this Relation, in which I am to diſcover, both what is in the Pope's mind concerning the intereſts of your moſt Serene Republique, and what good may be hoped for from him, or what hurt may be feared, if it ſhould pleaſe God to allow him a longer life than his conſtitution ſeems to promiſe. And if from the Confident and familiar converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a great Prince with the Miniſter of another, one may make a certain judgment of his intentions, I cannot believe any other but that your Signory may hope much from him, not things of that importance or quality that you have juſt need of, but at leaſt ſuch things as may ſuffice to maintain a peaceable co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence, and beget mutual Offices of Amity, ſtill accompani'd with the hearty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:135322:60"/> of beholding each others proſperity; For, in truth, I cannot ſay but his Holineſs treated with me with all kind of civility and good will; and as for thoſe things which be judged blamable, as ſuch actions, as having been per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps miſreported, he thought worthy of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; he hath ever done it with ſo much mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty and circumſpection, that I fear I ſhould erre ſhould I think otherwiſe: becauſe his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs hath ever ſpoken of your ſage Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in fair terms, having declared it was guided and adminiſtred with much Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Honeſty. Yet I took notice that he every day made ſome ſteps towards the deſign he had to oppoſe your Lordſhip's wills; and though he never changed his tone of ſpeech in treating with me, yet it was eaſie to ſee that he had given place to ſome ſiniſter im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, which abated the good opinion he was wont to have naturally for this State. His firſt words were upon my repreſenting to him the great and preſſing neceſſities your Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique underwent by the expences of the War; That your moſt Serene Lordſhips would not accept of thoſe Propoſitions that might in part have eaſed you, as that in ſuſpending ſome uſeleſs Religious Orders, which being once ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected had much diminiſhed the Publique charge, there being yet a new way to bring about this benefit, if the Republique would but ſuffer the Eccleſiaſtique Order by little and little to repair the loſſes they now ſuſtained by the alienation of their Eſtates, which might be
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:135322:61"/> done by revoking the Ordinance which forbad that Order to purchaſe any: upon which I ſhall not deſcant any more, having written ſo much already thereof, that your moſt Serene Lordſhips have juſt cauſe to be tired: But whatever I could ſay, it was impoſſible for me to perſwade him, but that this Ordinance would produce the bad effects he imagin'd. Sometimes he would take occaſion to complain, that there were ſuch diſputes and practiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the chief Commanders of the Army, that it hindred the Republique from being well ſerved, and that the moneys were not well adminiſtred, for that thoſe that manag'd it made ſo much profit themſelves, that it much damnifi'd the Publique, and that the ſame Commanders leſs careful of doing their duty than of making advantage, by way of Trade, of thoſe Commodities they tranſported to the <hi>Levant,</hi> were the cauſe that the Publique, which required the entire application of her Commanders, received a great prejudice there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by. All which things without doubt proceeded from the Mouth or Pen of the Prior <hi>Bichi,</hi> who to hide or cloke his own defects, expoſed thoſe of others. From thence the Pope took occaſion to complain, that the Republique in her ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities made her addreſs to none but the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolique Chair, and he for his part had no greater care than to furniſh them with aſſiſtance, and that if every Prince, according to the proportion of his power, would but do as much as the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> your Republique would be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:135322:61"/> provided both for the Defenſive and the Offenſive: and hereupon he began to make a long enumeration of thoſe Charges the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Chamber was ſubject to, and in this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, which was full of equivocations, as I ſent word to your moſt Serene Lordſhips, he was larger than enough to tire any one. He ſaid moreover, that at preſent the Peace was made between the two Crowns, and if they could formerly find out Treaſure enough for a War whereby to ruine one another, they might bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter do it to aſſiſt this Republique, which was become the Frontier of all Chriſtendom againſt the <hi>Turks:</hi> That your Signory ought to have a great and particular confidence in the <hi>French,</hi> ſeeing the partiality ſhe had ſhewed for them, when ſhe gave them all the ſatisfaction they deſired, tacitly alluding to what I related that hapned about the Ambaſſador's Rochet. And thus we onely loſt time in theſe diſcourſes at the laſt Audience, with little benefit to the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique: but it hath now been certainly made known to me, that if the Pope hath been hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſlow in performing that devoir, more incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent upon him than any other whatſoever, he will be yet ſlower hereafter, ſince he believes he hath gone farther than any other in his obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of oppoſing the common Enemy. This is that which makes him unwilling to hear of the ſending an Extraordinary Ambaſſador to <hi>Rome,</hi> imagining he would go with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign alſo of obtaining ſome extraordinary ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour: which, to ſay truth, I ſee the Pope very
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135322:62"/> little inclined to grant, not to ſay, obſtinately reſolved to refuſe it, becauſe, indeed, there is no mony. If they think he will erect any Banques to get it for them, I do not believe it; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, his Holineſs pleaſes himſelf in expending what ariſes from the few there are in ſuch things wherein he takes a great delight, as in Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and adorning of Churches, together with all accommodations for his Dwelling-houſe: and if he ſhould diſpoſe himſelf to do ſomewhat more than ordinary, I do not think he would uſe any other liberality but what coſts him nought, which is an increaſe of the Impoſitions of the Clergy of this State, which is known to be already ſo bare, that it hath nothing left but the bones: and that is juſt a helping of us with our own proper goods, although it be not deſired that we ſhould ſay ſo at <hi>Rome;</hi> for they would have us believe, that whatever belongs to the Prieſts in what Country ſoever, apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains to them. When the time of my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture approached, I found the Pope ſomewhat more mild. He gave thanks to God again for the Concluſion of the Peace, and teſtifi'd, that he had a better opinion of the affairs in the <hi>Levant</hi> for the future, alleaging the reaſon which I have noted, which was, that his heart told him, that your Republique would never lay down their Arms till they had defeated the <hi>Turks,</hi> and obtained ſome ſignal Victory over them. I gueſs, that he ſaid this to me, onely to encourage your Lordſhips, that ſo they might refuſe any kind of Treaty that might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:135322:62"/> to Chriſtendom; or perhaps he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded ſome League to himſelf, either with the Imperial Court, or that of <hi>Poland:</hi> I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not aver this, but I incline to believe the firſt rather, becauſe the Pope would hardly find any Princes in thoſe parts that would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in his promiſes; nor would they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage themſelves in any enterprize without a ſum in hand, that might aſſure them not to be deſerted, when they were once enter'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it. At my departure, after he had ſtood much upon my praiſes, wherein I had rather he would have been more ſparing, provided he had ſhewed himſelf more liberal in his favours towards your moſt Serene Republique, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned me to remember, to repreſent theſe four things to you: The firſt, That you ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſuppreſs, or take up thoſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences at the Tribunal of the Inquiſition at <hi>Padua,</hi> which are ſtill in conteſt, to the great ſcandal of all thoſe that hear of that matter: His Holineſs told it me juſt ſo, without any reflexion on it. But when your Signory reſolves to meddle with thoſe intereſts, there muſt be ſome important reaſon that ſhall induce you thereto. This order was very unpleaſing to me, becauſe it concerns a matter not ſuiting at all with my genious, and about which much noiſe hath been made.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, That the ſecurity of the Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in the <hi>Adriatique</hi> Sea ſhould be more carefully look'd after, for he complained, that there was no Trade in the port of <hi>Ancona,</hi> the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:135322:63"/> Merchants not being ſecure in their paſſage with their goods, by reaſon of the Repriſals thoſe Pirats of <hi>Dulcigno</hi> do make, who from time to time rove about to make their robberies, allarming the whole Coaſts of the <hi>Marca.</hi> He added, that if during the continuance of the War with the <hi>Turk,</hi> your Signory would ſuffer them to keep two Gallies in the Port of <hi>Ancona,</hi> it ſhould be done as ſoon as the Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron returned from the <hi>Levant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third, That it would pleaſe your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips to forbear interpoſing their judgments in matters Eccleſiaſtical, as they do from time to time, which offends and infringes the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Juriſdiction, and makes them run them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves imprudently into cenſorious inferences, not minding the diſgraces hapning daily there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon: He preſſed me much to oblige you likewiſe to moderate ſome of your Ordinances.</p>
            <p>The fourth, that your Signory would fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the Father Jeſuits with their protection in thoſe occurrences that may happen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſeeds of that hatred conceived againſt them, remaining yet in the hearts of ſome that do not well know them, it may be eaſie, but it would prove no act of generoſity, ſaid the Pope to me, to lay ſome ambuſh by ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumny or impoſtures againſt them, which are to be look'd upon with an indifferent eye, and being found out ſhould be repulſed. I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to obſerve punctually what his Holineſs had commanded me, and to repreſent what he deſired to your Lordſhips. You may be pleaſed
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:135322:63"/> to ſee and conſider wherein you can favour his Holineſs, having ſo great judgment as cannot erre; which concluded his laſt Audience, adding thereto his Paternal Benediction which he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon your Lordſhips and my ſelf, with his beſt wiſhes, and a preſage of victories and perpetual proſperities.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:64"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135322:64" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
